<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first part of youths errors. Written by Thomas Bushel, the superlatiue prodigall</title>
            <author>Bushell, Thomas, 1594-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17343</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4187</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114222</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849448</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849448</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14596</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17343)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14596)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1266:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first part of youths errors. Written by Thomas Bushel, the superlatiue prodigall</title>
                  <author>Bushell, Thomas, 1594-1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 173 [i.e. 165], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By T. Harper],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Letters, meditations and prayers.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The confession of a prodigall.</note>
                  <note>Pages 65-66 and 91-98 missing and 144-145 repeated in number only.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:14596:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14596:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> FIRST PART OF <hi>Youths Errors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by</hi> THOMAS BVSHEL, <hi>the Superlatiue Prodigall.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke 15.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I will ariſe and goe to my Father, and ſay vnto him, Father, I haue ſinned againſt heauen and before thee, and am no more worthy to be called thy ſonne, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London. 1628.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14596:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14596:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable and right vertuous, <hi>THOMAS,</hi> Lord Windſor, my very good Lord.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Excellent Peere,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ittle did I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, or your Lorſhip ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, to ſee my name come vnder the Preſſe;
<pb facs="tcp:14596:3"/>which as yet is to me a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſo likewiſe it muſt needs bee to your Honour a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, that knowes both my life and breeding, to haue nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther language, Latine tongue, nor, vpon my ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the helpe of any co-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iutor; but as it is written thoſe things which appear vnpoſsible to mans appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion,
<note place="margin">Mar 10.27.</note> are nothing to God vnſearchable wiſedome. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe your Lordſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> might ſuſpect the Authour for I miſtruſted my ſelfe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
<pb facs="tcp:14596:3"/>I had reade the ſaying, that God is able to make the dumbe to ſpeake,
<note place="margin">Luk. 7.22.</note> the blind to ſee, and the lame to goe; wherein he hath ſhewed the ſplendor of his diuine proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence on me baſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy creature, to ſee more clearely through my match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe offences; for that now I conſtantly beleeue, there is no forgiueneſſe without true repentance, nor no true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance without confeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, contrition, ſatisfaction, and amendment; which
<pb facs="tcp:14596:4"/>made me preſume to patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize the firſt fruits of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiredneſſe vnder your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips name; as a legaſie of my loyall dutie to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, preuention of others, and in my obedience to that good God,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 5.16.</note> who requires an open confeſsion, for a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique tranſgreſsion. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in if I ſhall verifie our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours words to giue <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. 22.21.</note> I muſt acknowledge vnder God your noble rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a monaſticke life, was the greateſt inducement I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb facs="tcp:14596:4"/>from mortaliſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my regeneration. So that if I haue mounted too high in ſheltring my weake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aboures vnder your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips vertues; let me beg a fauourable cenſure, and attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute rather forgetfulneſſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngratitude, than my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe to preſumption: for beleeue me (honoured Lord) had I not fortunately <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt your faire hand before departure, my zealous fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itie was ſo mixt with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>regs of mortalitie; that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb facs="tcp:14596:5"/>vpon my companion reuolt,
<note place="margin">Pro. 26.11.</note> I had fallen like a do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to his vomit and ruinated my owne ſoule. But thanks b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the diuine prouidence, by a ſhorter cut I haue met with contentment, ended my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, diſcarded my pleaſures and circled the earth. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt knowes my ambitio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was neuer higher then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> poore remote Caue or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert Cell, where if theſe illit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate-deiected lines ſhould reflect a likeing in you Lordſhips iudicious rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding;
<pb facs="tcp:14596:5"/>I am confident by Gods aſsiſtance, future en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eauours might edifie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ers: eſpecially when my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eregrination ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tand of your religious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>robation, whoſe honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le opinion I eſteeme more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en mortall creature; not for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at your noble apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n exceedes all men; but by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſon your internall fidelitie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quals the beſt of men; which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccording to my ſimple <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udgement carries a greater <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enediction and clearer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation
<pb facs="tcp:14596:6"/>of Gods fauou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then all other vertues: how ſoeuer if the tributary praie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of a ſinfull Beadſman ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> encreaſe your Lordſhips im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall glory. I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent God multiplies you honours daily.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your obliged and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted ſeruant <hi>THO. BVSHEL</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14596:6"/>
            <head>To my Chriſtian Brethren.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what I would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay in way of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition as alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether example, for that the holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>poſtle aſſures me I was not borne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my ſelfe, but for others; though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u may perceiue I haue confin'de my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſon from ſocietie of man; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue that I barre not the viſitation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man, but willing to edifie all men, farre as God ſhall enable my weke
<pb facs="tcp:14596:7"/>abilitie, and their patience; hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> intreating that the ſpectacle of y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſinfull brothers miſerie, may mort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your fleſhly deſires, and take ſo m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> compaſsion of your ſelues, as to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent future perils. I haue my rewa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you your glory: otherwiſe the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger's deſperate, as mine is damna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> without Gods vnſpeakable mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which my faireſt hopes cannot as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> beleeue he will ſo much remember <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to forget his iuſtice. O then ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sirs, if your owne conſciences acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> you, reſolue to follow the one, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the other; for aſſure your ſelues, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſident of my fatall afflictions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be an occaſion to condemne you at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> day of iudgement, if you obſtinat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neglect the ſame. But why ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> expect you will either read or m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:14596:7"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of them knowing the writings of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r Sauiour, the laboures of Apoſtles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d whole liues of ancient Fathers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e caſt aſide as ſuperfluous garments; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen a play booke is admitted to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe away the time: which, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard griefe I confeſſe, were my libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es; and, I feare, continue too much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ur ſtudies: yet for that my inuiſible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rments liuing vpon earth as <hi>Diues</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hell, and can at any time reſolue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe which doubts in the ſame, may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> an occaſion to extenuate your licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous appetites, that Gods name may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> glorified, your ſoules ſaued, and I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſatisfied.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO. BVSHEL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:14596:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Contents of this Booke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt part.</head>
            <p>THe Prodigall Sinners Confeſſion</p>
            <p>The Prodigalls Petition</p>
            <p>The Prodigalls Affliction</p>
            <p>The Prodigalls Contemplation</p>
            <p>The Prodigalls Prayer</p>
            <p>The occaſion of the Prodigalls reuolt from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> world</p>
            <p>The difference of a publique and priuate liui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> together with his reſolution</p>
            <p>The conference he had with a graue Diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> before his departure to a monaſticke life.</p>
            <p>His wofull experience of inſinuating fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers.</p>
            <p>The confeſſion of his diſobedience, with a tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> relation of his Lord and Maſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galls aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement concerning</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>The hopefull branches of Vni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities</item>
                  <item>The rights and profits belong the Church</item>
                  <item>The contents of Mariage</item>
                  <item>The crying ſinne of murther</item>
                  <item>The crying ſinne of Pride</item>
                  <item>The crying ſinne of adulterie</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14596:8"/>
            <head>To his louing Brother <hi>Edward Buſhel</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lomon ſayth, He that couereth his ſins ſhall not proſper, but whoſo confeſſeth and forſaketh them ſhall haue mercy. <bibl>
                     <hi>Prou. 28.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnknowne to your ſelfe nor the world, that I conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued a prentiſhip the ſuperlatiue Prodigal, either I am aſhamed to diuulge, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen God himſelf commands vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enalty of eternall damnation,
<note place="margin">Iam. 5.16.</note> yet it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14596:9"/>griues my very ſoule that euer I ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> occaſion to be recorded. But I ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> this my irrecouerable follie will p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent future ages for falling into fearefull a danger; otherwiſe as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> birth was miſerable, ſo their dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will be lamentable: which to me w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> rather aggrauate my ſorow, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> tenuate my torment, though in te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall affayres many bearers leſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the weight, and eaſe the ſurcharg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſufferer, but in ſpirituall none ref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the oppreſſed; eſpecially yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> diſſolute brother, who hath in a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſearched the records of heaue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for a Preſident to make his title <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hell vnqueſtionable:
<note place="margin">Exod 20.</note> as you may t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more perſpicuouſly perceiue by the dreadfull following lines. O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deareſt Microcoſme in nature, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14596:9"/>what vnwillingnes do I lay open my diſobedience againſt the firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, knowing my own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience pleads guilty in the higheſt manner, for debaſing his name, Eſſence, and Glory, below the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of a temporall Lord, a mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke Magiſtrate, or peſant Iuſtice, in honouring them more with cap and knee, then his omnipotent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that created me. But when I caſt my eye vpon the ſecond, there finde I a diſtraction of madneſſe, though I haue not worſhipped the molten calfe of braſſe, iron, ſtone &amp; the like; yet haue I done ſacrifice to the image of liuing clay, with that adoration as I made the female ſexe my godeſſes on earth, and left the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe of my time for the ſeruice of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14596:10"/>him that made me: howſoeuer touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the third I ſo much prophaned the Deitie of his name, that I made it my familiar diſcourſe, for which in iuſtice I am culpable of death. But as for the fourth I continually mixt my weake douotions with ſo many er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious pleaſures, that to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, I kept not one whole Sabbath for his gory: wherby I am debarred of claiming either loue, fauour, or mercy: but the courſe of perdition, which for ſurer violating the firſt, I was ſo ſparing in ſhewing either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence or dutie to my parents, that I ſeldome payed any tribute as I ought, whereby I haue deſerued not onely the ſhortneſſe of dayes, but the loſſe of their fatherly bleſſings. As for the firſt thanks be to God, I haue not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14596:10"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctually ſhed the bloud of any man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd whether it were not more for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eare of puniſhment by the decree of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nan, then the law of God, I neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an ſay nor iuſtifie my ſelfe; but to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny remembrance am free from that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rying ſinne: howſoeuer for the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enth, if I ſhould deny the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edgment of that deadly ſinne, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynt actors in my luſtfull recreation will cry out vengance on my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emnation: for we euer held it as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>port of pleaſure brought into the world by nature, and at the moſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ued in the ranke of veniall ſinnes: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut now it ſpeakes death vnto mee, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd I feare, no comfort vnto them, which for the eight you know in my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hildhood was guilty: ſo that I can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eit her acquite nor accuſe my ſelfe of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14596:11"/>any mortall fact: and as for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ninth, I canot plead ignorance, but t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my knowledge was neuer brough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the teſt before a ſeat of impartia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> iuſtice. Yet as I was, it is ten to on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that I ſhould haue proued more fleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> than ſpirit, more falſe than honeſt but certainly for the tenth I mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> confeſſe my ſelf guilty to all, either b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thought, or act, with delectation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> affection. Thus you ſee the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and ſinnewes of the whole la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> haue I broken, which makes m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> liable to eternall torture, death, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> damnation; God forgiue them tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were the occaſion. Yet if the mult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of theſe crying ſinnes were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>period of my transgreſſions, I migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue hope by the death and paſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of my Sauiour. But when I pond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:14596:11"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on the barbarous and inhumane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rriage vſed towards his mercies; it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tinguiſheth the light of comfort, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>our, or pardon, for God knowes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>am more worthy of death by his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath, then for violating he whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w of <hi>Moſes,</hi> in that I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ortall ſinnes againſt him that died <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r my ſinnes;
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.25.</note> by making the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oanes and ſorrowes in his paſſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e robe of ſhelter to my baſe wicked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d deteſtable pleaſures: for that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ar'd not proſecuting the life of my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rſed offences vpon preſumption of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s mercies, not ſearing his iuſtice; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or pittying his ſufferings: whereby haue exceeded the fact of <hi>Iudas</hi> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Senate of Iewes, for the one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayed him but once, I a thouſand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es: the other crucified him out of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14596:12"/>ignorance, I a million out of wilfulneſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> What aſſurement (deare brother) ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be expected by me that am worſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe whom I haue named, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dreadfull ruine of permanent perdit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zek. 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccle 5.</note> Yet you will ſay God is mercifu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vpon repentance at the laſt gaſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which cannot be denyed: ſo likewi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> my conſcience tels me hee is iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which will not be contradicted.
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.17.18.</note> Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> certainly without my repentance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall my tranſgreſſions, the Churc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may abſolue me,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eue. 18.</note> but not aſſure m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> And I ſhould vainly expect remiſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by any gho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tly fathers abſolution, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I continue in any one ſinne whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> lieth in my power to preuent:
<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.6.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the greateſt comfort of continuan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in all my calamitie was the ſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſaying of our Sauiour, that himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:14596:12"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d his Angels ioyed more at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nuerſion of one ſinner which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ely repents then ninty nine righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous. O with what an vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble happineſſe was this cordiall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſe to my afflicted ſoule; wherein miniſtred the application daily to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>freſh my ſad heart and weariſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſes; but at laſt it proued bitter as all in operation and digeſting. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen I ſearched into the miſtery of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>id ſenſe, there I found it was ninety <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine to one, that a wilfull ſinner ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er truly repented; otherwiſe you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould make God ioy more in a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll wicked mans life then a religious godly liuer: which brought me into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o fearfull a danger of deſperation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat had you or any other beene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n eye-witneſſe in the agony of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14596:13"/>my perditious ſoule, it would hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> made the flintieſt heart ſoone chooſe to wreſtle with a Lion then commit a mortall ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the immortall God which created him. Yet after a long debat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> betwixt hope and deſpaire, the preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of <hi>Saul</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Paul,</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled into me the happines of hope by reaſon his palpable crimes refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſome equality to my offences <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but at laſt his patterne left mee in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> darke Ecclips, for that they were er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors executed out of ignorance,
<note place="margin">Tim. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wilfully, and therefore obtayned re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion vpon his contrition. I the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> miniſtred to my deiected ſoule th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mercies conferred on <hi>Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lene:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uke 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> yet notwithſtanding ſmall wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my reliefe, for that her conflict o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:14596:13"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pentance did in a manner exceed others, and her tranſgreſſions but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of the ſeuen deadly ſinnes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hereupon I applied the thiefe on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Croſſe as my laſt refuge: but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere I ſaw apparant leſſe ſhelter: for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the rayſing of <hi>Lazarus</hi> from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue was onely a miracle to ſhew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at he was Chriſt the Meſſias;
<note place="margin">Luk. 23. Ioh. 11.</note> euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my conſcience telles me, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n paralleld mercy vpon the theefe,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.38.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as preordained only for that houre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be as a witneſſe of his wrongfull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nominious ſuffering, and not any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſurement of ſafety for vs to build <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n. Thus being depriued (as you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay perceiue) from all hope in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue of God by my diſobedience, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom all mercy by my matchleſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſumption, and from all comforts
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14596:14"/>in malefactours by my ſuperlati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tranſgreſſions, together with inwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> griefes of the ioyes I had loſt: a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the wofull exchange of heauen f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hell, brought me into that deſpera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> extaſie, as I fell ſuddenly on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ground in a trance, where diue iudgements of God reiterated to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> memory, that were executed alrea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vpon his deareſt ſeruants for leſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fences: which cloſed all the facu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of my body and ſoule into an o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſcure darkeneſſe: but thankes be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the diuine prouidence, that reſtore me ſoone after to my former tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility: and hauing recouered a ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible feeling, my oppreſſed heart d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to know whether his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were ſo ſeuere as my appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion led mee. I ſuddenly ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:14596:14"/>to my poore caue, God knowes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th troubled thoughts; for my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tions were eyther drowning or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cuting my ſelfe: yet thoſe aſſalts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſily repulſed by Gods aſſiſting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>miſſion, with the preſident of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and the like: but then opening <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> booke of the old and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, there I found our firſt parent <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>am,</hi> whom God gaue dominion the whole world,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.17.</note> yet for eating <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e apple forbidden though it was the intiſement of another, hee and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s poſteritie were extinguiſhed for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er.
<note place="margin">Num. 20.27.33.</note> Likewiſe <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> notwithſtanding they could obtaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y thing at Gods hands; yet for that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey ſomewhat doubted of the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e promiſed by God, they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tred for euer going into the land
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14596:15"/>of promiſe.
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.17.18.23.</note> Againe <hi>Saul</hi> whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> choſe to be the firſt King of his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, was degraded of his dignitie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> giuen ouer to the hands of an e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirit, for that he did but reſerue ſo certaine ſpoiles of warre, being co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to the contrary.
<note place="margin">Leuit. 10.2.</note> Beſides ſuddaine killing of <hi>Nadah</hi> and <hi>Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſonnes of <hi>Aaron</hi> for once offering ther fire then was appointed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> The ſtriking deade of <hi>Ananias</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sapphira</hi> for onely retaining ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> part of their owne goods by dece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">Acts. 5.10.</note> Likewiſe the iection of <hi>Cain</hi> and his linage fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſtraight vpon his murther.
<note place="margin">Gen. 7.10.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>Beniamin</hi> the onely ſonne of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> whom God loued ſo dearely,
<note place="margin">Gen. 4.2. Iudg. 20.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for one ſinne that was committed <hi>Gibeah</hi> vpon the wife of a Leu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:14596:15"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od deſtroyed almoſt the whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>be of men, women, and children; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith many other examples, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aring to claime any alliance of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> I ſurceaſed with repentance that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad them. O my deare brother, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſumptuous ſinners had felt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ck of my torture at the ſame inſtant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey would haue confeſſed in their earts, that God is ſeuere and iuſt as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is infinitly mercifull: yet my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ience alwaies aſſured me hee neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ft a ſinner that deſired truly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, without a ſinner forſooke him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich was ſome eaſe to my ſurchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed ſufferings. But the arch-enemy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f man continued his Rhetorickes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd applications of deſpaire, reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng alwaies to my memory theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the like herſe-like ſounding pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14596:16"/>of holy writ: if the righteo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall ſcarcely be ſaued, where ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vngodly and ſinner appeare?
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.17.18.</note> and iudgement begin at the houſe of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what ſhall the expectation or end wicked men be? howſoeuer I dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not in the mercy of my Sauio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but in my owne baſe and vnworth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> demerits; for that hee is certaine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> faithfull:
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.23.</note> if I hold faſt the profeſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of my faith according to the meaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which he hath giuen me; yet wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with Satans aſſaulting, my ſinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> afflicting, and feare of not obta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning Gods fauour, it transformed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from what I was, to the portrai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of an Anatomy; as the Inhab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tants neere adioyning to the ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Iſle can witneſſe. For thoſe tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> came to viſit me, out of charity pit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tied
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14596:16"/>me, and I in Chriſtianity grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed as much for their ignorance, which being by his ſacred plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure brought to deaths doore, and readie to yeeld vp the ghoſt in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amentable ſpectacle betweene hope and deſpaire; at laſt there appeared ſpirituall-wiſe an appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition of my own picture, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall ſonne,
<note place="margin">Luk. 15.</note> without intermiſſion to my ſoule and ſences, which did reflect ſo much internall comfort, as a woman in the agonie of her paines, ioies to ſee a manchilde borne into the world,
<note place="margin">Iohn 16.21.</note> and forgets her paſt ſufferings; euen ſo the dailie contemplation of this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall parable reſtored mee to that height of happineſſe, as it did more auert the dolour of griefe, ſorrow,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14596:17"/>and deſpaire, then all the felicity I receiued by preſidents in the ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and new Teſtament: but when my conſcience aſſured me the firſt part of his life I had acted to my eternall deſtruction, and that of neceſſity I muſt follow the ſecond to obtaine my redemption, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it would prooue infortunate and fatall, which hauing ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon the imbecillitie of my owne nature, the allurements of the world, and continuall aſſaults of Sathan, I feard it would prooue too ſtrict a captiuitie for mee to paſſe thorow: whereupon I plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, our Sauiour died for all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, yet my conſcience anſwered, it was for none but thoſe which truelie beleeued him in their liues,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14596:17"/>and vnfainedlie repented in their hearts, which made mee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er the dreadfull ſaying of Chriſt himſelfe,
<note place="margin">Rom. 9.27.</note> Few are the number that ſhould be ſaued. O affectionated Brother, that all my prodigall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences had beene transformed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to pious charities, my former plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures into penitent praiers, and my vaine diſcourſes into true confeſſions: then had I not liued a diligent ſlaue to Sathan,
<note place="margin">Iam. 5.16.</note> but a dutifull ſeruant to my Sauiour: which, God knowes, now the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of either ſo much ſounds re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate as makes me deſcend with a dolefull heart and alleadge my birthright by baptiſme. But like a ſoft aire it anſwered not elected by adoption; reiterating to my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14596:18"/>thoughts the preſident <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> infortunate <hi>Eſau,</hi> who found n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> place of repentance,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.17.</note> though he ſought it carefullie with teares But when at laſt I read the feare full ſaying of our Sauiour, Mani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were called,
<note place="margin">Mat. 20.10.</note> but few were choſen O what an immortall wound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gaue me; for my decrepit hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> enforced me to curſe conception birth, &amp; life, wiſhing the plague of Egypt had beene my copart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, rather than thoſe deceitful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pleaſures my companions, which made mee ſo incapable of creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, redemption, and election. I thus continued in this wofull ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle for the ſpace of two daies, not caring to miniſter either reſt, or nouriſhment to my weariſome
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14596:18"/>body, but did wholly contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate on my forlornd eſtate, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng to my ſelfe, How ſhould I know whether I bee elected or not? The ſpirit anſwered, either by a good life or true repentance, which vpon examination was ſmall comfort to me, hauing nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther performed the one, nor ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured the other. Whereupon finding my ſelfe by the allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Sathan, vanities of the world, and frailties of nature, brought into ſo deſperate, wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and dangerous caſe, that if I did not forſake my ſelfe, there was no ſaluation, but damnation: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his death and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which coniured mee by Gods permiſſion, faithfullie to reſolue
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14596:19"/>to diſcard all pleaſures, doubts, ſcruples, or feares, and wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon the ſweet ſaying of our Sauiour,
<note place="margin">Eſay. 1.18.</note> Though my ſinnes were as red as ſcarlet, yet hee would make them as white as ſnow; if ſo be my repentance proceed from contrition of heart during life; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe I might feare, miſtruſt, deſpayre, for I ſhould much rob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God of his iuſtice in depending<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vpon his mercy,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.22. Pſal. 85.10.</note> and damne my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoule with preſuming on his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, when himſelfe proteſteth they both kiſſe each other; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie his preſeruation from ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dangers in the world, and the aſſaults in this my conflict, hath made me reſolutely to ſet my reſt vpon the anchor of this hope,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14596:19"/>that if neither inward griefes nor penitent praiers by the mercies of our Sauiour cannot attaine vnto the ioyes of heauen; I will ſtriue to mitigate my torments in hell; but certainelie I am reſolued ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſuffer death, then commit any grieuous or wilfull ſinne: for I ſhould accompt my ſelfe more accurſed then either Heathen, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, Turke or Infidell, by how much my knowledge exceedes their ignorance, and his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence my baſeneſſe, in exhaling me out of <hi>Sodome</hi> to <hi>Zoar,</hi> from an euill bewitching Court, into a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull ſolitarie Caue, where no fraud, pride, nor deceipt inhabits. O my beloued Brother, if you or any other did but know the ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14596:20"/>happineſſe, which retired<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe bequeathes thoſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon Gods prouidence, and are reſolued to encounter tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by reformation. I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent the man liues not that deſires preſeruation of his ſoule, but would rather affect the ſolitarie continent life, then all the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of <hi>Solomon.</hi> Though I muſt confeſſe the firſt two months were both fearefull, dangerous and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate: but after repulſing the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lent alluſions of Sathan by theſe generall pleas to all his aſſaulting accuſations, alleadging, I both confirmed and acknowledged his words to bee true, that the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of my life neither had, nor could deſerue any hope, fauor
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14596:20"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pardon; and that I confidently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eleeued as he ſaid, it were impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble ſo many ſinnes ſhould eſcape <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>npuniſhed, hauing the ſame God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be iudge, which not onely crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, redeemed, and preſerued, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nowes how opprobrious and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ontemptible I haue beene to all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Lawes, Statutes, and Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ents, giuing credence to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ords from my heart, that euerie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilfull ſinne ſhould bee afflicted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith contrary particular torment, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onfeſſing that Gods ſacred iuſtice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſpected no perſons, but rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed euery man according to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſerts; and therefore hee might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt aſſured of mee when euer my Sauior was pleaſed to pronounce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is ſentence: for that I knew my
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14596:21"/>paſt life deſerued none other, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as for future, himſelfe warrant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> could merit no other. Yet in rega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gods vnſearchable prouiden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gaue me life after ſo many inh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mane tranſgreſſions, and bele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing the comfortable ſayings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſts owne words: thoſe thing which are impoſſible to man, we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no whit impoſſible to God,
<note place="margin">Mar. 10.27.</note> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that he deſired not the death of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſinner, but ioyes more at the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of one offender, then nin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie nine righteous. Beſides him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe had made mee more capab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of apprehending Gods hatred t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſinne, ſeueritie in puniſhment, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his bleſſings preſumptuouſly abu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed by my baſeneſſe. So that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were a monſter in nature, if eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:14596:21"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> did more offend the Deietie of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is ſacred name.
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.26. Ioh. 15.22.</note> For in commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng wilfull ſinne, I ſhould bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onfident it would trench againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Holy Ghoſt, attributing, hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>artly rewarded the prentiſhip of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny ſeruice in reuealing the naked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uth of my wretched eſtate; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſting vpon the faith of my ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, let him ſay what he would, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttempt what hee could, yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing ſhould allure mee (by Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſiſtance) neither to deſpaire, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffend my Creator more, but lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing ſoule, body, life and death, at his will and pleaſure; acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging my ſelfe, that if he had made me one of his number, I had iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerued it; and if his infinite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mercy ſaued mee, I muſt confeſſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14596:22"/>it were a miracle. Howſoeuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> would bee no longer diſobedient<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for that might prooue ingratitud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vpon ingratitude; I knowing what fauours God hath beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and now hee telling mee wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> offences I haue committed, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him, if hee were permitted to puniſh mee with bodily affliction and temporall croſſes the mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I were certaine of ſpirituall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. Thus is, and euer ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue my reſolution by the helpe of him that made me; for before I had fixed my heart, ſoule and ſences vpon this intire affection, neuer to be violated by any ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemes whatſoeuer. I was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually troubled with vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table thoughts, vnquiet feares, &amp;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14596:22"/>deſperate deſpaires: but now I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nde they are either leſſened, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe I am careleſſe of them: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch, that my inward faculties <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re mollified with a ſenſible humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty, to offer vp my morning and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uening ſacrifice, as a daily trib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f contrition, that euer I did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> end, and a trembling feare for to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffend; wherein one night aboue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll the reſt I cannot chuſe but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>art the rapture of ſo much ioy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat me thought my apprehenſion was transformed into another <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emiſphere, yet durſt not preſume <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n his mercy for feare of robbing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is iuſtice, by reaſon I could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er attaine to ſo high a pitch of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eleſtiall happineſſe, but in a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er orbe of teares and ſorrowes,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14596:23"/>to which I aſcribe God the glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> For when I my ſelfe was a co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panion of others, thoſe diſcipli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> poſternes were as heathen gree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to me, which now they proo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my daily delights of recreation, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall neuer be at quiet vntill I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obtained the period of that form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> felicity, which if nightly watc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, daily faſting, continuall pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or corporall affliction, ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> extract this vnparalleld comfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I will remaine conſtant, by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> permiſſion of God during life: o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſeruing ſo much time f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nouriſhing the faculties of natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that I may continue the longe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> But peraduenture ſome of yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lukewarme diuines will not ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mit of this life, though I am min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:14596:23"/>owne taskemaſter: yet I hope you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill not build vpon the Theory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> anothers opinion, more than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e practiſe of your Brother, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inioyned to loue you as his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ule; howſoeuer for my particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, may I neuer proſper in this my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>terprize, if all deuines ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake it not lawfull by thetorick, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eech, or traditions from <hi>Adam,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey would not reflect the leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ought of reuolt: for that I haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yned more knowledge, hope, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd comfort to my oppreſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ule in this one yeere of retired<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe, than fowre prentiſhips be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re; yet I take God to witneſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere is no man breathing that weth a more greate reuerence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their function and doctrine,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14596:24"/>then my ſelfe. But if his diui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> permiſſion amplifies a bleſſing my ſecond edition (as my hope depending) I will giue ſuch an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſured ſatisfaction, that your hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoule, and ſences ſhall ſay, God the author, and man ſubiect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> palpable erronious errours. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the meane time following <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſident of holy <hi>Dauid,</hi> my tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is in God, and therefore I feare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> what fleſh can doe vnto me.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Brother, though a deſert Beadſman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Thomas Buſhel</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:14596:24"/>
            <head>To the high and mighty mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Sauiour, God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and only Judge of Earth.</head>
            <head type="sub">The humble petition of thy diſtreſſed and deiected creature, the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue Prodigall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith trembling feare ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, That a poore Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant hath offended the Deitie of thy pious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, in what not, thats ill, with delectation of affection; whereby I haue loſt the birthright of creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14596:25"/>preſeruation, and redemption which my faireſt hopes canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preſume thou wilt breake th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whole courſe of thy iuſtice, in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mitting ſo many crying ſinnes t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eſcape vnpuniſhed. For that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt acknowledge with ſoule heart and conſcience, if thou ſaue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> me it is a miracle: and if thou re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fuſeſt, it were but iuſt iuſtice; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuring my ſelfe in forbearing thy chaſtiſing affection, I ſhall eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deſpaire of thy mercy, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of permanent puniſhment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for that the penſill of holy Wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which will not be violated,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.5. Apoc. 3.19.</note> hath plainely expreſſed, thoſe whom thou receiueſt, thou chaſteneſt, and that their long laughing muſt be turned into bitter mourning,
<note place="margin">Ioel. 2.12. Luk. 6.25.</note>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:14596:25"/>before they haue any true hope of thy grace, fauour or pardon. O then deare Mediatour! I beſeech thee miniſter dayly on me thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline correction:
<note place="margin">Pro. 3. Iob 5.</note> and when thou thinkeſt it meet, let my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward griefe be my ioy, the agony of death my comfort: but if thoſe will not penetrate my flintie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to make mee glorifie thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable bleſsings, and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend my baſe ingratitude; Grant mee ſweet Sauiour a feeling inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of torments due vnto the damned, that if then I may not without robbing thy Iuſtice ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine by thy Mercie a ſhare in thy ſufferings; Yet I humbly pray thee, let me be a ſecond <hi>Diues</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth; for admoniſhing my
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14596:26"/>poore Chriſtian brethren to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the like fall of ſo fatall a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and the rather, for that thou perceiueſt offendours bee not ſo much terrified by thy iudgements pronounced in holy Writ; as they are mollified at the ſight of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall creatures miſeries. Wherein it makes me feare Sathan by thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion hath a more predominate power, then thou that createſt them. All which I leaue to thy diuine Sacred will, and vnſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able mercie; begging pardon for my bold preſumption, or if thou pleaſe to make interceſsion,
<note place="margin">Mat. 8.8.</note> and ſay Amen to my petition.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:14596:26"/>
            <head>The affliction of a Prodigall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Deare and Immortall God! I thy abiects crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture haue ſo highly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended thy Deitie, Eſſence, and Glory, in prophaning thy Name, abuſing thy Bleſsings, and ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy Sufferings, that I dare claime no priuiledge by thy death, no comfort in thy promiſes, nor no fauour from thy mercies: but the rigour of puniſhment, the wrath of iuſtice, and reward of the damned. O miſerie of all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries what haue I loſt! thy Glory
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14596:27"/>that made mee, thy Sonne that dyed for mee, and thy Spirit that ſanctified me. Is there a creature from <hi>Adam</hi> ſo wretched? was there a child conceiued from <hi>Euab</hi> more miſerable? then I that haue loſt the ioyes of heauen, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſt the fire of hell. O my birth life and death, I am wrapt in ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, hauing ſmall hope but in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing, no comfort but in grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, nor any ioy but in lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. O thou falſe heart and curſed ſenſes, why were yee made to bring my ſoule in torture, and your ſelues in torment, to denie them will not auaile you, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect pardon is vnpoſsible, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe them will hardly mitigate them. O then deare Sauiour, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14596:27"/>I haue brought my ſelfe by ſinfull preſumption, to perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent perdition: yet let mee beg at thy hands the agony of indiuidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſorrow, which thou ordaineſt for the damned; that if then the ſpectacle of my deſerued maladie cannot diſſolue thy iuſtice into mercy, yet may mitigate my end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe miſery, and not die like a ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid dog void of ſence, knowing thou madeſt me the image of thy Creature.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:14596:28"/>
            <head>The Contemplation of a Prodigall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y God, Creatour and Sauiour of the world, was not I made thy image to ſerue and glorifie none other but thy ſelfe? How falles it out (deare Father) that I haue beene more contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible againſt all thy Lawes,
<note place="margin">Sap. 5.</note> Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and Bleſſings,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.5.</note> then a ſauage beaſt? I cannot beleeue it procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from originall ſinne, in that thy ſacred ſelfe ſuffered for ſinne; nor from my conception,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 33.</note> for that thou deſireſt my preſeruation;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14596:28"/>but altogether by Sathans aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, the worlds prouoking, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures betraying, and my owne ſtiffenecked tranſgreſſion. What reaſon then can my ſelfe or mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man conceiue, that thou wilt ſaue me, when I neuer truely ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, nor honoured thee? Art not thou a iuſt Iudge,
<note place="margin">Ier. 25.</note> as thou haſt beene a mercifull Sauiour? To plead weakneſſe auailes not, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe I dare not, nor wanting thy aſſiſtance I cannot. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then doeſt thou giue mee longer ſuſtentation, when thou knoweſt I haue deſerued damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?
<note place="margin">Fxod. 9.16. Act. 4.27.</note> Is it for that thou wilt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in thy mercies to increaſe my miſeries? Or elſe are not my ſinnes fully compleat for thy determined
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14596:29"/>ſufferings? Why, thou knoweſt Sathan offended thee but once, I haue euer, they both obey and feare thee, I haue neuer. What madneſſe then would it be in mee to preſume that thou wilt breake the whole courſe of thy iuſtice for my ſake? knowing in mine owne conſcience I haue loſt the benefit of thy redemption by my wilfull preſumption: otherwiſe I might bee confident through vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained repentance to haue aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſaluation by thy death and paſſion: which now grieues the intralles of my ſoule, in that I was ſuch a curſed reprobate to crucifie thee who ſufferedſt on the Croſſe to ſaue me:
<note place="margin">Mar. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> ſo that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to humane iudgement my
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14596:29"/>talent is eternall torment. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer I bequeath the diſpoſure of my deiected ſoule to thee,
<note place="margin">Rom. 9.15.</note> which ſhedſt thy innocent bloud on the behalfe of me. But why ſhould I being ſo baſe a creature reaſon with thee that art my maker, knowing the clay ought not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt with the potter. For it is in thy power and not in mine, to make mee a veſſell of honour or diſhonour. Therefore in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to thy vnſearchable Deity, I will ſurceaſe all diſputations, and endeuour to preuent worldly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations; that I may haue ſo much hope to be thy creature, as my beleefe aſſures mee thou art my Creatour.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:14596:30"/>
            <head>The Agonie of a Prodigall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y ſacred Creator, and celeſtiall Father, didſt not thou make me of running water and ruddie earth? Doeſt thou not ſee how Sathan aſſaults me? how the world inſnates me? and how my owne nature betraies me? O my God how then canſt thou but in pittie take compaſſion vpon me? knowing I haue no power to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent any of theſe precedent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, but by thy diuine proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14596:30"/>Wilt thou then leaue mee to my ſelfe, that I might appeare worſe miſerable than the beaſt which periſheth? O be more cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, for that thou madeſt mee thy image; caſt but thine eie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mee, and turne not thy face from me; then trie whether thou wilt denie thy mercy vnto mee: were not, ſweet Sauiour, my firſt parents ſinners? Did not thy ſelfe ſuffer for ſinners? and proteſtedſt thou deſireſt not the death of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Shall then the iniquities of my onely offences blot out the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thy immortal mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies? When thou art my aduocate, I the offender; thou my redeemer, I the debtor. Let mee not then periſh for want of thy protection,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14596:31"/>when it is not riches, nor honor, I would haue; O my Father, no! or releaſement of my miſeries I ſeeke; O my Father, no! or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen I beg; O my Father, I dare not preſume, no! nor any thing I craue; but the increaſe of penitent teares fit for tranſgreſſors, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes due to ſinners; O my Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, no! How then canſt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie me? when I ſue for no more, but what thy ſelfe hath aſſured me? O my Chriſt! are theſe the eyes that haue diſpleaſed thee; let them receiue no light through thee: is this the heart, which hath diſhonoured thee; let it bleed to death for thee Is this the fleſh which hath offended thee? let fire be her fuell by thee. Are theſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14596:31"/>the bones which haue brought me woe? let them bee burnt, and borne no more. Or are theſe the ſences which haue ſinned againſt thee? let them be a liuing ſacrifice to thee. O my God, I am rackt with griefe, that I cannot grieue; and perplext in repentance, that I know not how to repent. For to proceed after the worlds weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I ſuſpect thou ſeeſt their wilfull ignorance. And if I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thy Goſpels profeſſours, I feare thou findſt them full of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall, diſtraction, and worldly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation. What then (ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour) will become of me forlorne creature, that haue no reliefe? but ſinnes to ſuccour me, Sathan to aſſiſt me, and a guilty conſcience
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14596:32"/>to comfort mee: without thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſufferings make interceſſion for me, and accept thy Saints ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations for ſinners to thee; I ſhall be forced to curſe my conception, and wiſh my mothers wombe, had beene my tombe, to haue formed me a lumpe of fleſh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out life, or any creature but thy image; for then had I liued accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to creation, and not liable to eternall damnation. Yet, moſt mercifull and immortall father, ſhould my agonied ſoule ſuſpect to ſuffer ſhipwracke, when thou guideſt the ſterne? or deſpaire and die, when thou art liuing? or curſe her birth when thou art in being? O my God, rather let her taſte the tortures of hell, then be depriued
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14596:32"/>of life, and loſe her hopes in the ioyes of heauen, let then Sathan aſſay his beſt, and the wicked world her worſt, my deiected ſoule hath ſet vp her reſt in thee that made her to ſaue her; Lord I beſeech thee to ſay A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:14596:33"/>
            <head>The Supplication of a Prodigall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y God, my refuge, my mercy, how dare I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy greatneſſe, when the billowes of my crying ſinnes haue raiſd the wrath of thy Omnipotent perſon; who out of meere diuine loue to pious cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, createdſt me after thine owne image, redeemed mee being loſt, and in a word gaue mee all I euer had; yet haue I ſo much diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Deitie of thy glory, that I made the pleaſures of this life, my
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14596:33"/>Gods on earth, and now they are turn'de my tormenting accuſers of Death; O Sacred Father, bequeath the plagues of Egypt for my ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, rather then this deceitfull world to my portion, which hath not onely bred me diſobedient to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee that made mee, a trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour to thy Sonne that dyed for me; but ſacrific'de my owne ſoule to be the fuell of hell fire. O dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life of immortall death, what ſhall I tearme thee? the ſhape of a Chriſtian, which without thy Sacred interceſſion for thy neuer dying mercies, I ſhall remaine quickened with the fiend of hell, to future ages for euer. O do not thou ſweet Sauiour forget the pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of thy goodnes, though I haue
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14596:34"/>loſt the dutie of my obedience; but grant the ſame fauour to me, thou gaueſt the thiefe vpon the Croſſe, looke vpon the teares of my miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries with the paſſions of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and if neither griefes, groanes, ſighes, nor ſorrowes can appeaſe thy iuſt wrath: why didſt thou make mee? wherefore was thy death? whom wilt thou ſaue? or art thou another God now, then when thou wert mercifull to the oppreſſed, a Father of the godlie, and an aduocate for the damned if they repented. O then enrich my ſoule with a diuine ſorrow for my ioy, the agony of death for my comfort, that I may neither pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume of thy fauour, nor deſpaire of thy mercie; but haue thy great
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14596:34"/>Name glorified, thy Sacred death ſatisfied, and thy poore forlorne ſinner ſaued, Lord I beſeech thee, ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:14596:35"/>
            <head>¶ The Prodigalles Prayer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Deare and omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent God, I heere ſtand guilty of all the barbarous and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſinnes which Sathan can obiect againſt the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedſt creature liuing. For I haue preſumptuouſlie committed more riots and offences, then either Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, Pagan, Turke or Infidell, beſides treacherouſlie made thy name a cloake for my owne vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanie. Thus, deare Sauiour, haue
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14596:35"/>I liued a ſmooth factour for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, to the vtter ſubuerſion and depriuation of eternall felicitie, and purchaſed the reward of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation with endleſſe miſerie. Breake, O my big ſwollen heart, leſt a thunderbolt from heauen preuent thee. Guſh foorth into a flood of teares, thou Crocodile by nature, in being ſuch a curſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate to forget thy maker, a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell incarnate for crucifying thy Redeemer. Ah ſauage beaſt, could neither creation, redemption, nor dailie bleſſings mollifie my flintie heart to honour thee as a father, feare thee as a God, or loue thee as a Sauiour, but muſt ſo <hi>Iudas</hi>-like, ſacrifice thy image to the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, thy curteſies to crueltie, and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14596:36"/>thy redemption to my dreadfull deſtruction. O indignation of the Almightie, fall not vpon mee, though I haue ſowed the vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeed of <hi>Plutarchs</hi> aire for Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions to bite my fleſh, and ſnakes to ſucke my bloud. Yet, moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father, ſhould my miſerable ſoule deſpaire, when thy omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perſon died for deiected ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? Or can I preſume to hope, ſeeing thou haſt puniſhed thy dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſeruants for leſſe offences? Neuer (O Lord) in my wretched ſelfe, but by the vnſpeakable death and paſſion which is able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the ſicke, heale the lame, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the blinde, and helpe the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed to thee, I ſubmiſſiue come; whoſe ſacred wiſedome knowes
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14596:36"/>that man is rottenneſſe, his deſires vanitie, and life miſerie. Wilt thou therfore ſhew thy ſtrength againſt ſo poore a worme as man, that hath neither creation, preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor habitation, but by thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine prouidence? O then, deareſt Father, remit the execution of thy iuſtice; enlarge the liberalitie of thy mercie, and extend thy holie ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit on me thy loſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruant, that I may neither curſe my birth nor being, thou repent of thy creation or redeeming; to the end I might liue in thy feare, die in thy fauour, reſt in thy peace, riſe in thy pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and remaine in thy glorie. Lord I beſeech thee ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:14596:37"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> Earle of Derby.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y honored Lord I doe not know how far this my ſolitary life may trench into the diſpleaſure of your Lordſhips graue cenſure. Therefore I thought beſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend thoſe generall reaſons which were the occaſions of my reuolt from the world: aſſuring your Lordſhip it was not the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14596:37"/>fantaſie of my wandring thoughts,
<note place="margin">Gal. 6. Pro. 18.13.</note> but a ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my former tranſgreſſions, with an inward meditation of the ſmall time that God will ſtay for mans conuerſion or euerſion, made me bequeath the remainder of my daies to this priuate Cell, by your Lordſhips aſſiſting permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Yet peraduenture ſome will alleadge to your Honour, that this courſe of retiredneſſe is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commanded nor commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; what others out of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance may obiect, fat bee it from your Lordſhip ſo to iudge.
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.6. Socra. ſcho. cap. 18.</note> For it hath beene practiſed by the beſt ſort of Chriſtians euer ſince Chriſts time, with ſuch preciſe and ſtrict ſeueritie, as they did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14596:38"/>reſiſt all externall acts of ſinne, but chaſtiſed their bodies with corporall affliction,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.5.</note> which is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in the liues of the Apoſtles, by their much faſting, watching and praying Likewiſe Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtines</hi> conuerſion, and Saint <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romes</hi> approbation of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony</hi> the Heremites, beſides the diſcipline he vſed vpon his owne bodie; with manie other ancient Fathers, which for feare of being tedious, I omit. So that if theſe holie men were fain to vndertake ſuch ſtrait captiuitie for gaining of heauen, what puniſhment ſhould I endure for preuenting of hell,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.17.</note> whoſe whole courſe of life hath beene a race of errours: eſpeciallie when the ſpirit of God dailie
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14596:38"/>knockes at my heart to proſecute the ſame auſteritie: which giues mee a more cleare reuelation of Gods fauours, where now I finde the theorie ſo much to be true by practiſe, that I call God to witnes I am no more able to expreſſe the felicities I enioie, then remember the catologue of my paſt offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, let therefore other men thinke as they pleaſe of this alteration,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.3.4.</note> it ſufficiently contents me that the Saints in heauen reioyce at my conuerſion. For God hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken peace to my ſoule, my ſoule preacheth peace to my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, my conſcience ſings a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ſweet All-haile to my ſad heart: and ſhould the world, the fleſh, or the Deuill ſound all their
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14596:39"/>moſt powerfull inſtruments to plucke from this my reſolution, they may ſacrifice my fleſh vpon the worlds Altar, but my faith ſhal be ſo ſure found hanging vpon the hornes of this <hi>Sanctum Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> as my heart is confident that your Lordſhips former fauour conferd on me was preordaind to be a meanes of ſealing your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption by the death and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Sauiour, were your paſt tranſgreſſion red as ſcarlet; for that I am bounde to acknowledge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God your Honours affable curteſie eſtabliſhed my regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<note place="margin">1 Pet 4.8.</note> and what the reward is in gaining a ſoule,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.20.</note> beleeue not mee but the promiſe of Chriſt expreſt in holy writ. Humbly intreating
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14596:39"/>your Lordſhip ſo farre to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue your reſpect, as when any ſhall queſtion my fidelitie, aduiſe them to ſuſpend their cenſure till the fortunate, fatall, tribunall day of iudgement; which will decide the queſtion without malice. The rather for that each of vs were baptized with the ſigne of the Croſſe, and both endeuouring to hit the ſame marke though with ſeuerall ſhafts. But if it ſhould fall out to be knowne, that they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues continue in any one wilfull ſinne, your Lordſhip may boldlie giue no more credence to their language in points of Religion, then to a periured man in caſe of a triall. For as the Law will not admit of the one, certainlie God
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14596:40"/>will not allow of the other; whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the penſill of holy Writ confirms that the Diuell holds them as we by one ſinne as by a thouſand.
<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.</note> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which I leaue to your Honour graue iudiciall iudgement, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your euerliuing Beadſman,</hi> Thomas Buſhel.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:14596:40"/>
            <head>To the onely ſonne and bloud of my owne body.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued: the Lord thy God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct thee; thee to obey me vpon pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie of eternall puniſhment, that wilfullie breakes the couenant; if my aduertiſement agree with the penſill of the holie Ghoſt, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thou art free, I only bound; which to auoid the danger of my part, I haue, as God hath enabled my illiterate and humane appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14596:41"/>bequeathed vnto thee by my wofull experience, a briefe diuine, and morall way, how to proſtrate thy louing obedience towards God and man, for the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer preuenting Natures frailty, the ſafetie of thy owne ſoule, Gods glorie, and the diſcharge of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers dutie; that thou mightſt not curſe thy birth, I thy being, nor diuine prouidence repent of thy making; hoping the preſident of my late erroneous life, will cauſe thine to be religious; otherwiſe my iniquities will bee added to thy tranſgreſſions, though no eaſe to each of our ſufferings. Let there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy internall faculties of body and ſoule be zealous towards thy Creator in keeping his Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14596:41"/>with a trembling feare of violating the leaſt, and a willing deſire to performe them all; in ſo doing, thy mortalitie is ſure to bee ratified with immortall glorie. Let his iuſt iuſtice euer go before thee, and his infinite mercie will not faile to follow thee. Let thy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations be alwaies vpon our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours ſufferings; then thou canſt not be ſo ingrate as to forget his bleſſings, nor neglect thy duties. Giue thankes to thy maker for thy nights ſleeping, and morne wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, with humble deſire of his continuall prouidence for the day following; and at night call thy ſelfe to a ſtrict account of what good deedes thou haſt omitted; and what offences thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted;
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14596:42"/>who were the occaſions of the one, and neglect of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, from ſuch refraine, vnleſſe thou canſt command thy ſelfe, not they thee: but if they proceed from thine owne ſtiffenecked na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, condole thy infirmity, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtize thy iniquitie with continuall abſtinency, vntill thou findſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and religion to maſter thy paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and affection; by this means thou wilt euer after ſleepe in peace, continue obedient, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in ſafetie: but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, as thy conception was wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, ſo thy life will bee lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, thy death miſerable, and thy torments ineuitable. Let therefore thy beleeuing faith bee grounded vpon the rocke Chriſt Ieſus; for
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14596:42"/>that is the true Religion; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are toſt vpon the waues of time, proceeding rather from mens frailtie, then any ſetled veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Yet leſt thy conſcience ſhould be eclipſed, and thy continuance reuerted into the dreadfull danger of a lukewarme Chriſtian, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding ſo many graue Senatours of ſeuerall Religious opinions; I haue held it expedient vpon my death bed, and according to my engagement, as the ſoule of mee muſt anſwer the ſame at the tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall day of iudgement, to preſent vnto thy internall ſpirits theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited precepts. Let thy heart and conſcience bee incorporate to the bodie of Chriſts vniuerſal Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, performing ſo farre
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14596:43"/>as in thee lieth, all theſe preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which he hath enioined thee to obſerue, obey and keepe in holy writ; and when thy conſcience, together with thy ghoſtly Father, approoues of thy inabilitie, to bee capable of the Sacramentall mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, make a true confeſſion of thy life paſt, with an inward repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant contrition, that euer thou didſt offend, and a conſtant reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution by Gods permiſſion neuer more willing to offend: but ſuffer death rather then violate thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; as afterwards to commit a hainous ſinne, or wilfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in any other. This being zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſhe kept, God warrants thee ſaluation, who then will accuſe thee? thy conſcience cannot, and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14596:43"/>Chriſt hath proteſted he will not, if thou doeſt thy vtmoſt endeauor to performe thy couenant: and as for mans accuſation thou knowſt hee is arraind at the barre with thee, how can hee iudge or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne thee, when all his hope is vpon our Sauiours mercie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme himſelfe. But if afterwards thou ſhouldeſt wilfully continue repleat in any one ſinne, thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience reiterating daily the ſame, and yet wilt obſtinatelie perſeuere in hope of his mercy, I might iuſtly ſuſpect <hi>Iudas</hi> receiuing, and feare thy damnation; when the penſill of the holy Ghoſt hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, He that ſinneth wilfullie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter receiuing the knowledge of truth, there remaines no more ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14596:44"/>for ſinne, but a fearfull loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for iudgement. O then fleſh of my fleſh, let my preſent tortures preuent thy future torments; for I call God to witneſſe I now wiſh one of my limbs had periſht when I conſented to wilfull ſinne, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued martirdome when I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted mortall ſinne; doe not then perſeuere in offending, nor delay thy conuerſion, for I ſhould ſooner curſe thy begetting, than ioy in thy being, or hope of thy atchiuing to Gods Kingdome. Trouble not thy ſelfe with pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie, for feare of falling into the perpetuall puniſhment, but ſpend the remainder of thy daies in almſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds, faſting, praying and the like, for the ſurer preuenting of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14596:44"/>both, and gaining of heauen. Truſt alwaies in Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, then thy owne conſcience will be ſure to direct thee better then mens counſells; yet in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall negotiations, and how farre thou maieſt trench into temporall affaires, without preiudice to ſoule or bodie. Be vigilant to ioyne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies thy ghoſtly father in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion with thy conſcience, but let thy conſcience bee of the <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram;</hi> for he cannot ſaue thee, the other may condemne thee, though he muſt anſwere it if hee either neglect or direct thee wrongfully; howſoeuer his tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will be no mitigation to thy torment. Obey the King to the loſſe of life, fortune, wife or fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:14596:45"/>but let thy conſcience receiue no impreſſion contrary to its own direction: for if thy ſoueraigne be vertuouſly giuen, he will neuer preſſe thee; if otherwiſe follow thy Sauiours words, feare not thoſe that deſtroy the body, but loue and feare him which can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy both ſoule and body. Fight not againſt any Nation that doth baptiſe with ſigne of the Croſſe and beleeues the inviſible Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, without thou art commanded by thy Soueraigne or inuaded by themſelues; ſo ſhall thy hands be freed from the guilt of chriſtian blood; ſtand not ſo much vpon the title or theorie of religion, as the practiſe in religion; for what is a crowne without a Kingdome,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14596:45"/>honour without vertue, or lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning without perſeuering; neither hunt after the diuine and hidden myſteries of predeſtination, electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, deſtinie and the like; for in my conſcience they are left eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and as ſtumbling blocks for ſeeming-wiſe men to ſtagger at. Therefore reſt thy ſoule vpon this reſolution, that although the cauſes be not knowne to thee, yet vndoubtedly they cannot be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt, being preordaind by the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Iudge of all Iudges. Shew al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies a reuerent obedience to the ſupreme head of the Church vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſt Ieſus, and giue credence to their canon lawes, but not as canonicall ſcripture, though they were debated by the conſiſtorie
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14596:46"/>of counſels, and eſtabliſhed to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reall in the ſtrength of mans capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, yet they receiued an impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of mortall frailtie euer ſince the fall of our firſt parents; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer owe dutie to them all as la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures of holy fathers, but faile not to follow thoſe which thou findeſt plainely quoted in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or recorded in thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: ſo ſhalt thou offend none, but practiſe all that God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire at thy hands. And if the controuerſie in ſupremacie ſtartle thy fidelitie, choſe rather the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of ſcripture to decide the queſtion, than mans diſputation; ſo ſhall thy heart not onely haue the rock of Chriſt thy leader, but his diuine inſpiration vpon <hi>Peter</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:14596:46"/>the Apoſtle for thy ſupporter, and vnleſſe thou findſt it recald by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elation I would not aduiſe thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o beleeue tradition. Doe homage <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o God in all ſanctified holy pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, and giue due glory to all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aints and Angells, as inuiſible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reatures, already conſummated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Chriſt Ieſus. But thinke not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f meriting heauen, for then I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ertaine to behold thee in hell; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hough thou hadſt fulfilled the whole law, yet thy originall ſin would accuſe thee, thy preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion condemne thee, and Chriſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eath a witneſſe againſt thee, who then will ſaue thee? none; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut the ſentence of Lord haue mercie vpon thee: onely thus farre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hou mayeſt goe according to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14596:47"/>iudgement, and not dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from the diadem of his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Deitie, beleeuing through hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aſſiſting prouident compaſſion thou ſtandeſt in a more ſure cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of ſaluation then whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thou liuedſt in worldly perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, owe an obſeruant obedienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to thoſe that are elected in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> place of Gods miniſters, yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe with none but thoſe who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> liues are anſwerable to their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. In ſo doing thou wilt pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the ones vice and reape th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> others vertue: for thou canſt n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> expect to finde all true Leuit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when Chriſt himſelfe found o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in twelue a traytor. Giue place t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thy betters, reſpect thy elders, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially thoſe that are in author<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14596:47"/>and goe to law with no man but in thy owne defence; yet if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hou canſt not play thy part with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paſſion, acquite the ſtage, for thou hadſt better to loſe thy repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and reuenue than hazard thy ſoule and body. Be curteous to all men, hate no man, doe good to any man, eſpecially to thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat cannot requite thee. Honour old-age, reuerence thy ghoſtly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her, and if it be poſſible remaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hy ſelfe ſingle, but aboue all of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is part; ſo ſhalt thou be freed from ſuſpecting a third perſon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hough the ſacred integritie of the others fatherly friendſhip may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quall, yet nature will be iealous, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd make thee alwaies ſuſpicious, which in time might proue perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:14596:48"/>Deuote a daily dutie to the ſect of women, and when thou beholdeſt any whoſe ornaments are decent, commend them, if cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, requite them; if charitable, extoll them; if vertuous, adore them; but if vicious, loath them; if ambitious, ſcorne them; and if malicious, ſhunne them: ſo ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thou bee freed from the ones ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and ſhare in the others ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: for there is no ſuch compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as a diſcreet, religious woman which to my great comfort haue knowne the one, and to my ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged griefe the other. But i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thou appeare ſo infortunate, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to forſake the celeſtiall rites of a ſingle life, to obtayne the ſociety of a temporall wife; let her ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:14596:48"/>be the foundation of thy affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and thy conſcience debate vpon confirmation before thou conclude a reſolution, that God may honour the vnion, and your ſelues ioy in the coniunction, which if diuine prouidence bleſſe the fruit of her wombe, let thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward loue be equally deſcended to thy eldeſt as ſcripture hath commanded, and thy gentle corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction as occaſion ſhal be required: ſo mayeſt thou redeeme thy virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie in raiſing a poſteritie to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God by a fraternitie. But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all be ſure to let charitie be thy gentry, and humilitie thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; let loue be thy laurell, and loyaltie thy louer; let aduerſity be thy fortitude, and fortune thy flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer;
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:14596:49"/>let vertue by thy veritie, and patience thy paterne; let wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome be thy wealth, and reaſon thy ruler; let ſinne be thy enemy, and thy ſelfe her ſiſter; let truth be thy tongue, and temperance thy taſter; let iuſtice be thy iudge, and conſcience thy Iuror; let faith be thy father, and obedience thy brother, let children be thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and education their portion; let mercy bee thy matron, and meekneſſe thy minion; let curteſie be thy kinſman, and chaſtitie thy coſen-german; let virginitie be thy affection, and vtilitie thy aflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; let repentance be thy profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and prayers thy peregrinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; let confeſſion be thy contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, and contrition thy regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:14596:49"/>Let life be thy lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and death thy preparation. Let thy ſpeech be plauſible, and thy proteſtations irreuocable. Let thy ſtudies be celeſtiall, and thy ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes ſupernaturall. Let thy ſighes be Sacramentall, and thy groanes coëternall. Let thy diet be debility, and thy attire decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. Let want be thy infirmitie, and Will thy integritie. Let thy hope be heauenlie, and feare thy frailty. Let grace be thy guide, and God thy glory. Thus, in a word, thou pledge of my poſteritie, thinke, ſpeake, and deale with God, as if all the world did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thee, and liue, and conuerſe with man as if God ſaw thee. So ſhalt thou appeare the liuely i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:14596:50"/>of thy maker, the crowne of thy mother, the honour of thy name, and the repairing of the Angels. God leade thee by the hand, and a fathers bleſſing goe with thee, as thou perſeuerſt in the practiſe of theſe precedent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:14596:50"/>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:14596:51"/>
            <head>To his louing brother <hi>Edward Buſhel</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eſt beloued, to anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilate your leaſt ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition of my fidelitie or ſelfe-wild imbecili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in this my retirde pleaſing life, I ingenuouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that mutuall fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ioyned with inward ſpiration to glorifie God is beſt pleaſing, moſt accepted, and greateſt rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. So that I am confident a publique religious life is better than any monaſticke priuate li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:14596:51"/>by how much virginitie is eſteemed aboue mariage; yet the leaw warranted to be honourable, according to the Apoſtles words. If thou doeſt marry thou doeſt well, but if thou canſt abſtaine, 'tis better. So likewiſe if tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> canſt liue priuate without wilfull ſinne, it is well, but if thou canſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, it were better. And where he ſaith, better to marry then to burne;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.9.</note> euen ſo my conſcience aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures me that it is better to liue pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately without ſinne, than burne publiquely in ſinne; for you know in the one there is hope of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but in the other certaintie of damnation. Which reduc'de mee to apply for experiment this ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ary courſe to prohibite mee from
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:14596:52"/>former follies, and preuent futur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perils. For you know from min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> infancie I ſo much naturally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in a male-contented life, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our parents diſciplinde gentle cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to withdraw me, fearing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was bewitched. Likewiſe in the height of my prodigallity, both your ſelfe and others were wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes how I then made triall at a poore fiſhers habitation, which God knowes would haue long continued had not my popula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> name beene knowne; yet in thoſe dayes ſuch was my childiſhneſſe, that more fear'd the preiudice of my baſe reputation then the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of my Sauiour: like ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting <hi>Pilate</hi> which beleeued the innocencie of Chriſt, howſoeuer
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:14596:52"/>to ſatisfie the Iewes, crucified him.
<note place="margin">Luk. 23.14.</note> Beſides, for almoſt three yeeres, you know, I was toſt vpon the waues of time in expectation of a familiar companion, who at laſt to my great griefe vnfriendly left mee, for no other reaſon I could imagine, but that he would verifie our Sauiours ſpeech;
<note place="margin">Mat. 20.16.</note> 
               <hi>Many that are firſt ſhall be laſt, and the laſt firſt.</hi> So that it is no new fantaſie, but hatching from my cradle as God knowes &amp; ſome particular friends that my determination was long agoe bent to leaue the world, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny my ſelfe, regaine the time, and follow him, were it within the caues of the earth, if his Diuine pleaſure allotted mee; But what through the rawneſſe of yeeres,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:14596:53"/>natures frailtie, and inſtigation of others, I remain'd ſo long with taking leaue of my houſhold, and ſtriuing to ſatisfie the humours of mortall friends, that almoſt my vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall hope was turned into deſpaire of immortall glory. But thankes be to the Diuine prouidence, my own conſcience is enlightened by the Goſpel of Chriſt to warrant mee his mercies, will heare my ſupplications from a poore Cell, as hee did <hi>Ionas</hi> in the Whales belly.
<note place="margin">Ion. 2.1.</note> So that, if now I ſhould reuolt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing had a yere of vnparallel'd ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, for either temporall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune or fear of corporal affliction, I muſt account the offence vnpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable; when the penſill of holy Ghoſt hath dictated the ſame by
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:14596:53"/>theſe irremarkeable fatall words; <hi>If wee ſinne wilfully,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.26.</note> 
               <hi>after the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the knowledge of the truth, there remaines no more ſacrifice for ſinne, but a fearefull looking for iudgement.</hi> Therfore I hope by Gods permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, your beliefe of my fidelitie will expell all doubts, ſcruples, or feares, knowing that I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed theſe lines to enſuing memorie as a recorded wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe on the contrarie againſt mee at the Day of Iudgement.
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.21.</note> In the meane time let him that is tied to loue you as his owne ſoule, perſwade your diligent ſearch into the world without par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialitie, and then I dare boldly ſay, you will find nought worth lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, no fortune worth valuing,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:14596:54"/>nor no pleaſure worth following but he that firſt made you: in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience then, he ought onely to be lou'd, valu'd, and ſeru'd. For my owne part, I by woefull experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence haue found it; you by tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from a brother may ſhun it. Let not then others ends, ſet a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> end to your owne happineſſe, no natures frailtie barre the fruition of your future felicity; but be ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to curbe the one, and ſcorne the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; in ſo doing your conſcience ſhall ſay, I was your friend, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your flatterer, as mine muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies acknowledge you a father more then a brother. Yet giue me leaue louingly to chide your wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe; ſince by Diuine proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence I haue rebuked my igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:14596:54"/>Your cauſes of diſcontents its knowne riſe early; will you therefore keepe them in perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all waking? Thoſe croſſes that ſtand betwixt you and happines, are mortall; muſt you then make your ſorrowes perpetuall and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal? The way to ſhorten them is to ſleight them, and the beſt meanes to mitigate them is not to minde them. I by experience doe ſenſibly feele it, you by practiſe may bee ſure to finde it. O then, gentle brother, let not griefe for a wilderneſſe,
<note place="margin">Mar. 8.36.</note> preuent your birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in Paradiſe; for vnder cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection (deereſt Sir) if you cannot brooke a temporall misfortune, in my conſcience you will neuer at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:14596:55"/>to a ſpirituall bleſſing: when our Sauiour and all his Elect are witneſſes againſt you;
<note place="margin">Mar. 10.24.</note> yet I muſt confeſſe your afflictions are grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then mine, though my ſinnes are a thouſand for one of yours. Howſoeuer not equall in deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, nor diſaſters to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, therefore ioy as they did in calamities, that you may bee found a Coſin-germane to <hi>Iob,</hi> ſhewing alwaies true Faith by your Workes, otherwiſe were you my Father, as you are my Brother, I ſhould forget nature, and greatly feare you haue no ſhare in Chriſts death. Pardon, deareſt heart, if I haue ſoared too high, it is in your power to clip
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:14596:55"/>the wings: but God knowes I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme your ſoules ſafetie, more then man or mortall felicitie. All which I leaue to his Diuine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence and your perſeuering goodneſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:14596:56"/>
            <head>To the Religious and Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lady, the Lady <hi>Elizabeth Willoughby.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Beadſman fearing the diſtance of place, and diſpenſation of wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, might cauſe a reuolt from your Ladiſhips former welwiſhes induc'd mee to recommend theſe weake lines, as an Antidote to preſerue me from the ſhipwracke of your diſpleaſure; whoſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous ſocietie, I euer honoured more then temporall felicitie; for that I was daily an eye witnes of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:14596:56"/>your pious charitie; religious diſcourſe, and noble hoſpitalitie, which makes mee preſume the goodneſſe of your chaſte diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wil rather condole my misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of inward griefe then attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute diſcontinuance to the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of nature or want of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimoniall affection; eſpecially hauing ſo much conference with a graue Diuine before my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as your Ladiſhip may more perſpicuouſly perceiue by theſe following lines; wherein I ſpar'd not the reuealing of my woefull tragicall life to his iudiciall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation; humbly intreating him, that as I had opened the bowels of my miſeries, ſo hee would impart the trueth of his
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:14596:57"/>knowledge. Whereupon with a modeſt and ſolemne countenance deſired my age, who replied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſixe and twentie, he then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to expreſſe his ſorrowes, that ſo young a man ſhould haue tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched into ſuch lowd offences, yet queſtionleſſe if contrition did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from my heart, there was no doubt but vpon true repentance God would forgiue mee. Citing the parable of the Prodigall;
<note place="margin">Luk. 15.</note> the preſident of <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diuers others, for confirming Hope, and preuenting Deſpaire He thus hauing ended, I gaue him much thankes for his fatherly counſell, aſſuring his reward was celeſtiall not temporall; wiſhing it might ſtand with his occaſions,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:14596:57"/>leaue, and liking to heare mee a word, who ſeemed to bee more willing then I was readie; at laſt imparted vnto him that I preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a retired ſtrickt Monaſticke life, would be the ſafeſt and ſureſt hope to depend on; for by ſuch meanes I fhould not onely auoid ſinne, the occaſion, but diſcipline my ſelfe, and the rather for that I had affection to the life from my infancie. Beſides the often drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming what ioy I found in it; inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating my conſcience daily reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated the ſame; and that if I did continue wilfully in any one ſin, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here was no foundation for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine mercy to build on;
<note place="margin">Heb. 10</note> which the world, cuſtome, and frailtie of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had prohibited mee from the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:14596:58"/>one, and induc'd mee to the other, as by my confeſſion he knew too true. Yet by no meanes he would not giue way, alleaging the life was neither lawfull, requiſite, nor honeſt, for that it was not allowed by the Lawes of God to cloiſter vp my ſelfe: nor admitted by our Church, expreſſing Scripture, that I was not borne for my ſelfe, but for others; and that my prayers could not bee ſo much auaileable as when two or three were gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together. But if theſe reaſons might not diſſwade mee from my intended reſolution, yet the vow of mariage prohibited me, though it was ſolemnized in the rawneſſe of my youth; by reaſon I had promiſed before God to forſake
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:14596:58"/>father, mother, and cleaue vnto my wife, aſſuring mee I ſhould neuer haue his conſent, nor hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they allotted ſuch bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beares to fright the poore Laitie. Whereupon I roſe vp (God knowes) as a man going to the gallowes, or like <hi>Iudas</hi> that betrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Sauiour, and thus accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my weake apprehenſion replied: Where hee expreſt cloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering, and that man was not borne to himſelfe, but for others, I beleeued it; aſſuring him, my ſelfe neuer meant it, but onely to turne thoſe purple robes of prodigalitie into an Hermites weed; denying none to viſite,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8.</note> but willing to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct any ſo farre as God would
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:14596:59"/>enable mee; promiſing future life ſhold be anſwerable to my ſpeech, and where he ſaid, prayers are not of that force, as when two or three were gathered together, I confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it; if ſo be they were all ioyn'd with inward ſpiration to glorifie God, otherwiſe they rather hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red then furthered, citing the firſt chapter of <hi>Ionas</hi> for my preſident. But touching the lawfulneſſe; I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged that our Sauiour praye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alone: the Apoſtles wandred i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſheepskins alone,
<note place="margin">Tim. 8.2.</note> whoſe liues we ought to follow, intimating the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aduice, My Sonne come out of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill company. Beſides, the word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our Sauiour,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.29.</note> 
               <hi>If thy eye offend pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it out;</hi> much more (in my opinion caſt off the world. And for marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:14596:59"/>where he ſaid I muſt leaue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, mother, and cleaue vnto my wife, I could not deny it, replying vnto him, that if I was to leaue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother for a wife, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely I was to leaue father,
<note place="margin">Luk. 9.23.</note> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and wife for Chriſt: eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly himſelfe expreſſing, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by three Euangeliſts;
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.37.</note> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were not worthy of him, if I would not: as it did more tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arent appeare by the ſeueritie of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur Sauiour, who would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it one of his Apoſtles to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orme the dutifull rites of a ſonne,
<note place="margin">Luk 9.62.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bearing his owne father, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e called him: much leſſe the rites <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f marriage. Yet he ſuddenly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vered, that both Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Church hath forbid the ſame
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:14596:60"/>without it were by conſent, and that but for a time; which made mee breake into a kind of paſſion, with theſe words vttering; Had our Sauiour ſaid to the man, hee ſhould not taſte of his Supper though inuited,
<note place="margin">Luk. 14.20.24.</note> for that his excuſe was the marriage of a wife. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, where hee ſaid, <hi>No man ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing put his hand to the plough, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> looking backe, was fit for the king dome of God:</hi> Notwithſtandin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hee intreated but ſo much time a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to take leaue of his houſhold. Be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſides, had God ſaid, Man was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> glory of his Maker; the woma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the glory of the man, the man th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> head of the woman, and yet ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not the head priuiledge to ſerue h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Creator, without conſent of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:14596:60"/>feet; intimating vnto him, that miſerable was the bondage to ſoule and bodie, if they were not called both at one time. But ſeeing the holy Apoſtle had not allowed it, I aſſured him I would doe my endeauour to gaine her conſent; howſoeuer I reſolu'd him I ſhould rather depend vpon the mercie of my Sauiour for that offence,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.17.</note> then continue more in offending; and follow the preſident of holy Saint <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eromes</hi> Confeſſion, where hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith, If his father ſtood weeping <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n his knees before him, and his mother hanging on his necke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inde him, and all his brethren, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſters, children, howling on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de to detaine him in ſinfull life with them; he would fling off his
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:14596:61"/>mother to the ground, deſpiſe all his kinred, runne ouer his father, and treade him vnder foot, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to goe to Chriſt when hee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him; and thus wee parted, proteſting vnto mee, though him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe would bee as neuter, yet his prayers ſhould be alwayes perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for my good ſucceſſe, hoping the like fauour from your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the rather for that I receiue ſo much inward comfort, and your vertues no preiudice. But when I had imparted to my wife, the dolourous griefes my heart ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained, alleaging that neither her eſtate, perſon, nor any temporall thing lining could eaſe my ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char'd ſufferings, for that they were immortall &amp; inuiſible;
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.</note> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> if
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:14596:61"/>ſhe pleaſed, hauing diſcloſed my ſorrowes to her ſecrecie, as either diſpence with my perſon, or elſe bee content to lead the ſame Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſticke life and leaue the world; In ſo doing our ſoules ſhould bee ſurer ſaued, my heart better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, God more glorified, no man iniur'd, if ſhee were ſatisfied. And to auoid ſuſpition of diſloyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the holy Sacrament ſhould te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie my integritie. Yet nothing would preuaile, alleaging her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage was for loue, not for wealth; for perſon, not for picture; which I knowing her words to bee true, my heart pleaded ingratitude if I left her, and my ſoule whiſpered ruine if I continued. But in the end, conſidering with my ſelfe, I
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:14596:62"/>was bound to obey the Creator more then the creature,
<note place="margin">Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.12.</note> and ſhe to obey mee, rather then I her, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when it tends to the glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God; but (honour'd Lady) that were too great a bleſſing for mortall creature, to haue two hearts contracted, and both vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in one diſpoſition; which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolution reduc'd mee to leſſen my former reſpect,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.30.32.</note> and obſeruing whether thoſe alluſions would extenuate her fond affection; which in proceſs of time wrought ſuch an impreſſion, as ſhee grew tractable to my diſpoſition; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſecretly ioyed more then a Generall that gaines a conqueſt by ſtratageme. Aſſuring your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhip, if the prayers and admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:14596:62"/>of the one, can make the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther immortall, her ioyes are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall, and our nuptiall eternall; which ſpirituall-wiſe prooues the greater affection according to the firſt inſtitution, as will hereafter more at large appeare, if God giue a bleſſing to my ſecond Edition. In the meane time I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate my ſelfe vnder the chaſtitie of your pious vertue and fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cenſure, reſting conſtantly your ſeruant, faithfully your lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and eternally</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Beadſman,</hi> THO: BVSHEL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:14596:63"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Worſhipfull, his indeered Friend, Sir</hi> Matthew Gary.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orthy Sir, knowing you to be of a Noble, free, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fable diſpoſition, makes me to feare ſome Paraſite might worke an impreſſion vpon the goodneſſe of your nature, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I haue preſumed to bequeath theſe experimentall lines, as an Antidote to preſerue you from the aſſault of familiar Flatterers; For when my ſelfe was entring into af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectation of popular applauſe, I
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:14596:63"/>choſe mee an old ſtagger of the times, as a boſome friend to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe my ſecret thoughts, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the courſe of the world; but hauing made knowne my fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall humor, hee ſeem'd to bee ſo much delighted in my vaine glorious ſpeech, as perſwaded me they were but tricks of youth, and ſutable to others, which ſoone kindled the fire of my affection in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the flame of Prodigalitie: for of my ſelfe I was prone by nature, but being back't proued a maſtiue curre; yet after the period of one yeeres experience, I aſſur'd him I much doubted, that my ſoule and bodie muſt anſwere for my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de, bribing, drinking, and wenching; deſiring his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:14596:64"/>whether it were not better to leaue off ſeruice, by reaſon cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome had wrought ſuch a priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that I ſhould hardly bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal'd, liuing among ſo many that were addicted to the ſame follies; and that my ſelfe ſpent more idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then I got lewdly; but his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to mee was like ſome inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Stateſman, that applaudes his Souereigne whatſoeuer hee ſayes, be it right or wrong; not for that their Iudgements are weake, but by reaſon their hopes, fortunes, and greatneſſe depends vpon the frowne or fauour of them. Euen ſo, this Sycophant, in expectation of pettie curteſies, gaue way to what my fantaſticke humour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired; guilding ouer the fouleneſſe
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:14596:64"/>of my vices, with thoſe pleaſing delights; that my pride was but fit for the place, and equall to my fellowes; For drinking, it was but according to my betters, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from others; for my bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing they were but gratuities pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by my predeceſſours, and as for my wenching, they were only errours of youth bred by nature, and ſubiect to all men. But touching my reuolt from ſeruice, by no meanes hee would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, alleadging I might profit my ſelfe, pleaſure my friends, and help the diſtreſſed. Thus did this cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atriſing Matchauill ſooth mee vp in all my loathſome pleaſures, till at laſt I told him I was credibly enformed that the world laugh't
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:14596:65"/>at me; who preſently replyed, It was but the liuery ſhee gaue to all men, intimating, if I would but continue one yeere more, my ſelfe ſhould ſo much goe beyond the ſpungie braine of common know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that humanitie would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue their crueltie into curteſie, alleaging it were Romane like to ſpurne at the frowne of fortune, and in ſleighting the calumnious tongues of men, I was more then heroicall: Which eleuated my weather-cocke diſpoſition into laughter and action, vntill, I had both equal'd the dog to his vomit, and ruinated mine owne ſoule. Wherein, Chriſt knowes, I now daily wiſh the plagues of Egypt had been my delights, rather then
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:14596:65"/>he my aſſociate, or thoſe my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions. For I call God to witnes, I would cancell the debt I owe to nature, but to call in the errours of my former follies. O then, ſweet Sir! let the infortunate ſpectacle of your friend, preuent the danger in your ſelfe, and beware of theſe ſmooth factors for the Deuill, whoſe inchanting wordes I feare doeth hazard more young mens ſoules, then the originall ſinne of nature: Hoping my late repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance will extract a timely refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, if you finde cauſe by the faithfull friend your owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:14596:66"/>
            <head>To his approued beloued M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iohn Eliot</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ample teſtimony of your true affection to wards my Lord <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulam</hi> Viſcount Saint <hi>Albans,</hi> hath obliged me your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant. Yet leaſt the calumnious tongues of men might extenuate the good opinion you had of his worth and merit: I muſt ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly confeſſe that my ſelfe and others of his ſeruants were the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of exhaling his vertues
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:14596:66"/>into a darke eclipſe; which God knowes would haue long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dur'd both for the honour of his King, and good of the commonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie; had not we whom his bounty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urſed, laid on his guiltleſſe ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders our baſe and execrable deeds to be ſcand and cenſur'de by the whole Senate of a ſtate, where no ſooner ſentence was giuen, but moſt of vs forſooke him, which makes vs beare the badge of Iewes to this day. Yet I am confident, there were ſome Godly Daniels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs; howſoeuer I will not mention any for feare of attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting more then their due, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending others; but leaue the ſequel to their owne conſciences, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an beſt iudge of innocencie. As
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:14596:67"/>for my ſelfe with ſhame I muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite the title, and pleade guilty; which grieues my very ſoule, that ſo matchleſſe a Peere ſhould bee loſt by ſuch inſinuating caterpil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, who in his owne nature ſcorn'de the leaſt thought of any baſe, vnworthy, or ignoble act, though ſubiect to infirmiries, as ordain'de to the wiſeſt: for ſo much I muſt aſſure you was his hatred to bribery, corruption, or ſymmonie, that hearing I had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiu'de the profits of firſt fruits for a Benefice, which his pious cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie freely gaue, preſently ſent to me, and being asked of his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, I ſodainly confeſſed, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon hee fell into ſo great a paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that repli'de, I was curſed in
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:14596:67"/>my conception, and nurſed with a Tiger for deceiuing the Church, threatning I ſhould be no longer his ſeruant; for that one ſcab'de Sheepe might infect the whole flock. Yet notwithſtanding, vpon my ſubmſſion, the nobleneſle of his diſpoſition forgaue me the fact and receiu'de me into fauour; but neuer could obtaine a ſpirituall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing afterwards: which makes me certainly beleeue they that mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter'd thoſe helliſh pils of bribery, gilded them ouer, not onely at firſt with a ſhew of gratuity, or in the loue of courteſie, but waited the opportunitie of his neceſſitie: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it had beene impoſſible to haue wrought an impreſſion. So that by ſuch ſtratagems the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:14596:68"/>men may proue weakeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all officers; for thoſe whoſe conſciences are innocent of mitigating iuſtice, either by bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, gratuity, friendſhip, fauour or courteſie, let him caſt the firſt ſtone and be canoniz'd for a Saint vpon earth. But the report goeth, that it is the policy of other States, when once the ſubiect groanes vnder oppreſſion, to ſelect ſome man of worth for allaying clamor of the vulgar, and congratulate the giddy multitude: which if his misfortune were ſuch, he was not the firſt, nor, I am confident, wilbe the laſt. So that in time it may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect ſome comfort to you and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that honoured him in their hearts, but not with their lips.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:14596:68"/>
            <head>To my Chriſtian Brethren the Ofſprings that proceeds from Vniuerſities.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued Brethren if you haue paſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, Ceremonies, and degrees with ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prou'd allowance by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon lawes of man to take the orders of Prieſthood, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Teacher, Paſtor and Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, which is the moſt worthy, honorable &amp; bleſt title confirm'd on man. Let not then (Deare
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:14596:69"/>brethren) my affectionate aduice be diſpleaſing, in perſwading your diligent reſolutions to ſearch the lawes, ſtatutes, and commands, which God both requires and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects at your hands; for if any of you vndertake the tuition o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoules, and then by the neglect o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your duties, there ſhould periſh ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, woman, or child, you are to anſwer for their ſufferings,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 23.</note> though no eaſe to the parties grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: So that as the dignitie of your profeſſion doeth excell the power and authoritie of Kings, Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, or Monarches; euen like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe their perils, hazards, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are equall to their greatneſſe by how much the one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; but the bodie temporall
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:14596:69"/>and the other Charge of the ſoule eternall. O then, gentle Sirs, let me intreat you for my poore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns ſake, Gods glory, and the ſafegard of your owne ſoules, ſearch narrowly into the fraile diſpoſitions &amp; conditions of your owne natures, and then ponder whether your abilities are of that efficacie and power to diſcharge ſo noble a calling, without degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the title, perill to your ſoules, and loſſe of our poore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſetting aſide the preſident of others, which I pittie ſome, feare diuers, ſuſpect the beſt. Yet I hope there will bee found many righteous <hi>Abrahams,</hi> chaſte <hi>Lots,</hi> godly <hi>Daniels,</hi> and patient <hi>Iobs.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, wee of the Laitie are in
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:14596:70"/>great danger, if the Clergie ſhould be loſt: for how can the bodie liue when the head is dead. Firſt, then deare brethren, let mee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you to follow the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe, Looke before you leape, read and conſider vpon the oath requir'd by man; next, examine your hearts if you can keepe the ſame which is expected by God; then, whether you are in loue and charitie, whether more fleſh then ſpirit, more addicted to pleaſures then deuotions, more delighted in worldly trifles, then heauenly treaſures, or whether more for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenue of the place, then Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and profit of your brethren. For if any of thoſe temporalties haue gained the vpper hand, yet it
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:14596:70"/>were weakeneſſe to attempt, but madneſſe to vndertake, vnleſſe you can command them, not they you. Otherwiſe, your ſoules are in danger, and they infortunate that are planted vnder your iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For beleeue it (hopefull Sirs) you cannot ſerue God and Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.13.</note> which thoſe vainely expects remiſſion, whoſe liues be not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to their profeſſion: for if the Deuills ſhould omit their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations, yet the poore ſoules, which periſh vnder their tuition, will cry out vengeance for their condemnations, and God is iuſt, as he is mercifull; So that I feare their language, <hi>Doe as I ſay, and not as I doe,</hi> will not protect them. Yet, worthy Sirs, you perceiue the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:14596:71"/>was honorable from the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, and the reward is glorious aboue any, if you liue anſwerable. But on the contrary, miſerable, wretched, damnable to your ſelues and others that neuer iniur'd you; ſo that it is better to bee an open wicked man, then a luke-warme Chriſtian Diuine; for the one ruines but himſelfe, the other ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards many, yet I had rather be no man then either of them. Wherefore, deere brethren, if vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mature deliberation, you finde your ſelues able to encounter thoſe enemies, which originall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and cuſtome hath claim'd a priuiledge, goe on boldly in the celeſtiall enterpriſe, and take theſe precepts along with you, as a help
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:14596:71"/>to your pious indeauours. Let the ſenſible faculties of your hearts be holy, religious, and zealous to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, with an inward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to edifie your charge, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the directions of Chriſts Catholike Church expreſt in holy Writ, not making any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference or reſpect of perſons. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them publikely, admoniſh them priuately, rebuke them ſharpely,
<note place="margin">Iam. 2.9.</note> and if thoſe will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call them, proclaime it openly, without fearing the diſpleaſure of any humane creature. For they are not worthy to bee Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that either diſtruſts in their Generall, or feares their Souldiers. But aboue all let me intreat you to be mindfull of Baptiſme, The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:14596:72"/>and viſiting the ſicke: For the firſt eaſeth your profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; the ſecond teſtifieth your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrities; and the third diſchargeth your duties. For as it confirmeth their ſaluation or damnation; ſo likewiſe it remaines the higheſt pinacle of your profeſſion: and if it be poſſible (adopted Sirs) enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine no wedlocke, but rather ſtriue to curbe nature with ſpare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of dyet,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.27</note> then ſatisfie the fleſh to vſe ſuch helpers. For your ſelues had need bee well grounded with inward ſpirations, nay in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner gods on earth that vndertake ſuch boſome friendes, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms the weightie charge which will bee requir'd at your hands; hoping your owne innocencies
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:14596:72"/>will neuer bee tempted to appeare in any ſpirituall preferment by the way of <hi>Sinon Magus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8.18.</note> or helpe of his coadiutors: for ſurely thoſe are neuer conſecrated by God, nor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by Lawes. How then (gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Sirs) in your owne conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces can they abſolue, baptiſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, or miniſter the Sacrament, but with a trembling feare of murthering the ſoule, like a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants conſcience that is imbru'd in blood. O then you anointed branches, bee not perſwaded by a mould of clay to trench in ſo great a crime, knowing your ſelues as yet vnſpotted. In ſo doing,
<note place="margin">Matt. 12.50.</note> Gods Name will bee glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, your brethren edified, and
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:14596:73"/>your owne dutyes diſcharg'd; which will remaine preſidents to others, ioy to your parents, comfort to your friends, and happineſſe to your Soules.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:14596:73"/>
            <head>To my wel-wiſhed Chriſtian Brethren, the Laitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F any of you are ſo infortunate, as to detaine the Rights and Profits, which was ordained by God for the maintainance of the Church and members therof; Let mee beg vpon my knees, as with teares I write it, that you make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, contrition to God and man. For if your conſciences pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudicate they are wrongfully kept backe, and yet willfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:14596:74"/>can it bee denied but that you rob God of his Iuſtice, if you expect ſaluation by the death and paſſion of our Sauiour; though ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit you will plead preſcription by Act of Parliament, and that it was and is lawfull for you to receiue, continuing ſo long in deſcent from your anceſtors. Yet, my deare Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, I pittie your weake, Right, Title, and Intereſt; for that it was not warranted from Heauen, but by Gods permiſſion confirm'd in Hell. So likewiſe you may plead damnation from your forefathers for foure thouſand yeres together, which is the more ancienter title, and ſurer to deſcend, if from your hearts proceed not repentance. Howſoeuer, fearing you ſhould
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:14596:74"/>ſuſpect ſpleene or imbecillitie: Let mee intreat you to fearch the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of holy Writ, and if there your ſelues find God pardon any one man that robbeth the church, without it were in ignorance, or ſatisfaction by vnfained amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, remaine as you are. But on the contrarie, looke vpon the dreadfull death of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Actes 5.5.</note> for detaining ſome part of their owne goods by deceit from the Apoſtles: much more you, that not onely take your own, but other mens; when Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſaith,
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.21.</note> 
               <hi>Giue vnto Caeſar that which is Caeſars.</hi> And if God would not ſpare his owne Tribe for one offence, certainly (deare Brethren) hee will not omit you which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:14596:75"/>perſiſt in the ſame:
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.21.</note> for that hee is a iuſt Iudge; as hee is a mercifull Sauiour; but peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture you will obiect, the inducted partie is more vicious then vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, more wicked then religious; howſoeuer it is the ſuſtentation of his birthright, and ought not to be diminiſhed. But aſſuredly himſelfe and thoſe are accurſed that inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted him, by how many ſoules periſh with his careleſſe neglect. O, beloued Brethren, if you would but ponder with your ſelues of the ſtrickt account which will be required from you and them at the day of Iudgement; I durſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage my life, there is not one true Chriſtian, but would rather chooſe to bee fed himſelfe, wife,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:14596:75"/>and family, with the almes of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, then liue wrongfully on the tythes of Laitie; for queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, as they nouriſh the bodie, they ſtarue the ſoule. All which I leaue to your owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, praying daily for reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:14596:76"/>
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:14596:76"/>
            <head>To my vnmarried Chriſtian Brethren.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eſt beloued Sirs, if you be not ſo fortunate as to performe your chaſte ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle liues,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> according to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles words, which placeth your ſelues next vnto God, but muſt of neceſſitie haue the vnion of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond helpers. Let mee, your wel-wiſhing Brother, aduiſe each of you to entertaine diuine religious thoughts in the daily contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your choice, before you at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt ſo weightie, and great a
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:14596:77"/>charge, which will be demanded at your hands, otherwiſe it may ſeeme a hard and ouer-ſtrict capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie in being bound and thrall with the cares and humors of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: for if it ſhould fall out that any of you doe meete with more bone then fleſh, more fleſh then ſpirit, your liues will alwayes bee moſt miſerable and wretched,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.28.</note> as by woefull experience diuers of your predeceſſours can informe you; that for one houre of their folly, being a fault committed without malice, and by meere o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-ſight; yea many times to obey the aduice of Parents, they brough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> themſelues into a perpetuall bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage: Which accuſtomed miſery (deare Brethren) proceeds from
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:14596:77"/>a fraile imbecillitie of nature, and want of ſpirituall diſcipline; they hauing not grounded themſelues vpon the fundamentall points of marriage. For beleeue me (gentle Sirs) if that your chiefeſt and only end bee not to auoid fornication, and a deſire of procreation to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God by a mutuall ſocietie, your Nuptialls were neuer ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niz'd by him, nor allowed by his lawes. For it were impoſſible, if God had a hand in the coniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that euer there ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed either iealouſie, malice, rage, or any other miſerable condition. But it may be, ſome will reply, that the Scripture confirmes all marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages are made in heauen: So li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe you know Chriſt died for all
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:14596:78"/>ſinners, yet few are the number that ſhall be ſaued,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 20.16</note> by reaſon the one wants, either beliefe, a good life, or true repentance, and the other omits performance accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the firſt inſtitution, which makes both dangerous, fearefull, and infortunate, for that humane creature rather <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> depends vpon the weakeneſſe of his owne ſtrength, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> then Gods promiſes; the allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Satan, then the bleſſings of our Sauiour. O then, my vnited brethren, let neither beauty allure, honor tempt, luſt prouoke, wealth encourage, nor parents compell, for they are all both imperfect and fatall, without you ſweetly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uper them, by reducing their extreamities into the chaſtitie of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:14596:78"/>vertue. Likewiſe, deare Brethren, there is another charge impos'd, greater then the former; whereof you muſt haue an eſpeciall care to edifie your wife, children, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily in the commands and ſeruice of God. For if any of them periſh by your neglect, the ſoule of you muſt bee ſure to anſwere for it, which grieues my very heart to behold ſo many of our predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors runne the hazard of eternall perdition, by this one tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in parents. For moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly they neuer thinke ſo much of the mutuall loue in glorifying God, as the reuenue of wordly profit, and temporall honor. Nay, I haue knowne ſome parents will marry the wiſe to the foole, which
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:14596:79"/>makes themſelues prooue tyrants to the of-ſprings of their loynes, for a little wealth to binde the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to the dead; but aſſuredly, howſoeuer it is carried in the ſight of men,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 5.13</note> they are accurſed before God, and thoſe infortunate that muſt ſuffer the bondage, who at laſt will cry out vengeance on the parents that begot them: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> which is the greater crueltie, but iuſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Wherfore (beloued Sirs) if I were worthy to aduiſe, there ſhould none follow the parents humours, yet pleaſe both parties according to the lawes of God, which not any is to obey further. Let then your ſelues but mitigate your fond and childiſh affection; your parents ſuſpend their raſh
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:14596:79"/>couetous diſpoſitions, vntill yeres and experience haue indued you with reaſon and religion to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend your fathers counſell with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repentance.
<note place="margin">Ezek. 1 20.</note> By this meanes the iniquitie of your fathers will not light vpon your ſelues, nor yours vpon your fathers, but each of you ſhall receiue ioy, the other comfort, all pleas'd, and God glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:14596:80"/>
            <pb n="153" facs="tcp:14596:80"/>
            <head>To his Chriſtian Brethren <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F any of your hands haue beene wilfully guiltie in ſheding the blood of your Chriſtian brother; let me humbly craue for appeaſing Gods iuſt wrath, and ſafegard of your owne ſoules, that foorthwith you abdicate all ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les, doubts, or feares; and retire your ſelues vnto ſome waſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>art, or religious Monaſterie: there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>editate on the crying ſinnes you
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:14596:81"/>haue committed, what a great God you haue offended, and what torments you haue deſerued; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying dailye to your deadly wounds the ſalue of ſighing, grones, ſobbing, teares, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſorrowes, accounting each of your ſelues not worthy to liue,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.17.</note> nor inhabite amongſt Gods crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Otherwiſe, dearely beloued, I ſhould ſooner beleeue there was no hell, then ſuch a tranſcenden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſinne will bee admitted into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; for you ſhould much rob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God of his ſacred Iuſtice, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting ſaluation by his death and paſſion, without your hearts and vitall parts penetrate a proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of bleeding ſorrow in lieu o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> contrition; which to make th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> trueth
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:14596:81"/>more perſpicuous, let mee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>treat you to ſearch the penſill of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oly Writ, &amp; if there you find God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ardon any one man (though they were his anointed) without ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue and vnfained repentance, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euer afterwards to commit a hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous ſin, nor wilfully any other, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut remain'd to their dying dayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the mournefull melodie of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, watching, and praying; yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld not all theſe ſubmiſſions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ontritions, nor petitions, extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uiſh the hatred hee bare to ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umane a ſinne; but would pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh them temporally, though in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e multitude of his mercies ſau'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em eternally. O then, vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate brethren, ſeeing the caſe is ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euitable wretched, betake your
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:14596:82"/>ſelues to the ſame true repentan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for preuenting the danger of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> dreadfull a ruine; and I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent you will be reſtor'd,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 33. Iohn 20. Sap. 21.</note> thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the fact is fatall, yet 'tis finite, at Gods mercie infinite. But on t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> contrary I lament your miſerie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pittie your calamities, and fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your deſtinies; for certainely h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that would not ſpare the root, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vpon ſuch auſtere contritions, it much to be doubted he will neu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forgiue the branches vpon leſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſubmiſſions.
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.21.</note> And thoſe Diuin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which ſhall aduiſe you to a mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhort and eaſier way of humilia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on, I am aſſur'd in the end, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> will finde them not your friend but your flatterers, for they da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not warrant you: Yet by leadi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:14596:82"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e remainder of your liues ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rely, according to this preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, God himſelfe protects you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth in the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, with theſe words, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill not be violated; That all ſins <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon true repentance were pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able;
<note place="margin">Luke 12.10.</note> but the offence againſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oly Ghoſt: and which is more, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oteſteth he neuer forſooke a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 18 23.</note> without firſt a ſinner forſooke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m. O then (diſtreſſed Sirs) can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u beleeue but God is mercifull, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e doeth condemne you, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou may be ſaued if you are truely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rrowfull: why ſhould you then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tertaine a thought of deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, or bee perſwaded by mortaliſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtay your conuerſion; though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey ſhould alleadge ſuſtentation,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:14596:83"/>yet the bloodie ſinne crieth for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and God expects tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> contrition, or elſe no remiſſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But peraduenture ſome will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect that the Iurie hath acquite them, or a Kings fauour pardo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Admit they haue; the one power is but temporall, the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence eternall,
<note place="margin">Luk. 12.5</note> and for the othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they may diſcharge the perſon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conceale the crime, but not fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the King of Kings, nor your own conſciences, which I appeale <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for your future comforts, God glory, and diſcharge of my Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian dutie. O then, forelorn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sirs, breake through the viole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> temptations of earthly creature accounting thoſe friends traitor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe wiues <hi>Ieſabels,</hi> and thoſe ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:14596:83"/>baſtards, that ſhall deſire to detaine you one houre from the fruition of your apparent redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<note place="margin">Reu. 8.3, 4, 5. Luke 5.52. Iam. 2.13 Mat. 9.13</note> In ſo doing the Angels are conſtant to make interceſſion for your reſtitution, and God will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer deny abſolution, ſeeing his greateſt glorie is magnified by your inward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:14596:84"/>
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:14596:84"/>
            <head>To my Chriſtian Brethren <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F any of you, my beloued, hath ingendred with the roote of that originall ſinne,
<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.8.</note> called Pride; let mee, the fatall vaſſall of the Chriſtian world, perſwade a ſuruey in the whole fabricke of your <hi>Microcoſmos;</hi> for that now the prodigall pleaſing pride of my youth ſounds the dolefull tune of deadly damnation, as I feare your
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:14596:85"/>ſelues continuing will equall my maladie, if not exceed my miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; which to mee will rather ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauate ſorrow, then extenuate my dolour. Wherefore, I beſeech you for Gods cauſe, and ſafetie of your owne ſoules, bee no longer ſtiffe-necked, nor ſelfe-will-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited in ſo high an offence, as not onely depriues you from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, but bequeaths you to end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe miſerie; which if the ſpectacle of my irrecouerable calamity, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not mollifie your deteſtable ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie: Search but the penſill o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> holy Writ and there you will fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> legions of Angelles abdicated o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their dignities for the ſame offence Beſides;
<note place="margin">Iudg. 1.6.</note> millions of your progen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. Nay more, my adopted bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:14596:85"/>I dare boldly ſay not one man that ſprang from the loynes of our firſt Parents, was euer ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into Gods kingdome, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his humilitie verified our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iours words, to become ſo inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tent of pride as a little child.
<note place="margin">Mat. 18.4, 7.</note> How <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen, deareſt Sirs, can wee that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he branches expect more mercie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen our forefathers,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.21.</note> when Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot onely confirm'd the contrary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n his life of humanitie, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eal'd the ſame by his ſacred Word to all his Apoſtles, as an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red marke of thoſe that ſhall bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ected his ſeruants. O then, hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> belou'd, let not fraile nature de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de, intiſing world bewitch, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niſhing honour ſeduce you; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen your tortured brother fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warnes,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:14596:86"/>warnes, humane reaſon prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites, and God himſelfe forbids vpon penaltie of eternall damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Who then will ſaue you, when Chriſts death, your owne conſciences, and all his Elect are Iudge, Iuror, and witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you; None (my belou'd) but Lord haue mercie vpon you I by woefull experience groan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnder the burthen, though God knowes my outward ornament alwayes exceeded my inward fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties; yet ſo much conſenting, a I feare daily repenting will hard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> extinguiſh helliſh tormenting. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> then, you (clayie tabernacles) mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my miſeries your timely preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and be not ſo in loue wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Wilderneſſe,
<note place="margin">Mark. 8.36.</note> as to loſe a Paradiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:14596:86"/>nor ſo much diſhonour your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, as any longer to crucifie your Redeemer. But let innocent Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie raiſe you, pious Prayers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore you, that Chriſts death may be effectuall for you. In ſo doing my afflictions may be mitigated, your dangers preuented, and all our ſhipwrackt ſoules ſaued.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:14596:87"/>
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:14596:87"/>
            <head>To his Chriſtian Brethren <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F any of you haue permitted betraying nature to inact ſo dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſinne as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable Adulterie, let my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent calamities preuent your fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture miſeries; otherwiſe I ſhall be certaine to condole your deaths, as I am confident you will curſe your births: for when you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that loathſome ſinne of luſt, you waken the indignation of
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:14596:88"/>Gods iuſt iuſtice; witneſſe your owne conſciences. VVill yee then perſiſiſt in offending, vpon hope of his mercifull ſuffering? O my deare Brethren, I might ſooner beleeue the Deuill ſhould bee called, then any of you cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen without ſo true a reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as your contrition ſhall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the deteſtation before God and man. Otherwiſe, according to my poore iudgement, your conuerſion hath no foundation for Chriſt to conſecrate his pious abſolution. What your Genius may out of Rhetoricke po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, or ſelfe-wil'd fidelitie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate a more eaſie way of ſuſtentation by his death and paſſion; Yet I feare thoſe that
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:14596:88"/>depend vpon ſuch Diuinitie, tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches too neere the Diademe of his Sacred Maieſtie, for euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing remiſſion by his miſerie,
<note place="margin">Iam. 2.13 Pſal. 85.10.</note> in regard God himſelfe aſſures vs his Mercie and Iuſtice kiſſeth each other. But peraduenture, ſome of you will not deny to reply, the wordes of my wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe; That which is bred in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he bone, will neuer out of the fleſh. Howſoeuer I now find the Apoſtles ſaying to be true, He that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ues in the fleſh dyes in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it; For it ſpeakes death vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee, and I am perſwaded (vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ontinuance) damnation to each <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f you. O then, co-partners, let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y too late vicious affection <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſe a timely depriuation; for
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:14596:89"/>when I beheld (by diuine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence) the naked trueth, there I found his fatherly commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had indued man with the facultie of reaſon to bridle ſtiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neckt nature. Beſides, vpon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamitie ordain'd him matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall vnitie for auoiding incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie. But ſearching into the chaſtitie of ſauage beaſt, I loath'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my ſelfe, and hated the inchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; which ſo ſure as there is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, each of you muſt doe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> like either in this life, or bee for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ced in the other to your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation without redemption. O then, I beſeech you, that an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the imaginarie creatures of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Maker, bee a little more mode<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then the brutiſh beaſt, that Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:14596:89"/>may ioy in your creation, and reward your ſoules with ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Otherwiſe, as your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions were wretched in the wombes;
<note place="margin">Prou. 1.24.</note> ſo I feare preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate torments will follow your tombes. Wherefore then, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized Chriſtians, will yee bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny longer deluded with wicked <hi>Ieſabels,</hi> or betraying <hi>Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lechs?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 18.23.25.</note> When GOD himſelfe proteſteth you may yet bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, if you doe but truely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.
<note place="margin">Luk. 5.32</note> What father could haue ſaid more?
<note place="margin">Matt. 9.13.</note> What Sauiour would haue demanded leſſe without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying his Eſſence to ſatisfie your baſeneſſe? I appeale to your own conſciences, whether any of you that knowes the danger, and yet
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:14596:90"/>will perſeuere in ſo heinous a ſin, can expect remiſſion by his death and paſſion: Howſoeuer, God forbid, that I ſhould foretell your palace to be in hell. But if ſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will not penetrate, curteſies nihilate, chaſtiſements mollifie, nor future torments terrifie; giue mee leaue to miſtruſt, deſpaire in your atchieuing to the Paradiſe of Heauen. O, infortunate Sirs, if your greatneſſe pleads protection,
<note place="margin">Act. 10.33, 34.</note> remember God reſpecteth no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, if your cuſtomary preſidence pleads preſcription;
<note place="margin">Iudg. 7.</note> remember the burning of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah;</hi> and if his mercies confer'd on <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> allures your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocations; remember his Iuſtice puniſhed legions of your proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors.
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:14596:90"/>O my beloued brethren, it grieues my verie ſoule, that our Sauiours compaſſion towards one offendour,
<note place="margin">Rome. 2.</note> ſhall be made a ſhelter for millions to continue in offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, when his iuſt Iuſtice execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon thouſands for ſuch tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, will hardly bring any to a true ceſſation, till the vice haue left them, not they it. Therefore I muſt conclude with Gods owne words,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 22.12.</note> 
               <hi>I will exerciſe Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in weight, and Iustice in meaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
